<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Authority xmlns="http://www.records.nsw.gov.au/schemas/RDA"><ID control="SRFileNo">07/0742</ID><ID control="AR">367</ID><ID control="FA">313</ID><ID control="AR">416</ID><ID control="AR">490</ID><ID control="SRFileNo">18/0267</ID><ID control="AR">573</ID><ID control="SRFileNo">SR2023/166</ID><AuthorityTitle>Premier and Cabinet</AuthorityTitle><Scope>Premier and Cabinet</Scope><Status><Submitted><Officer>Chris Eccles</Officer><Position>Director General</Position><Agency agencyno="10">Premier and Cabinet</Agency><Date>2011-07-01</Date></Submitted><Approved>2011-10-20</Approved><Issued><Agency agencyno="10">Department of Premier and Cabinet</Agency><Date>2011-10-24</Date></Issued><Applying extent="part"><Agency agencyno="10">Department of Premier and Cabinet</Agency></Applying><Submitted><Officer>Amanda Jones</Officer><Position>Chief Operating Officer and Deputy CEO</Position><Agency agencyno="6990">Infrastructure NSW</Agency><Date>2018-06-08</Date></Submitted><Applying extent="whole"><Agency agencyno="6990">Infrastructure NSW</Agency><StartDate>2018-08-23</StartDate></Applying><Issued><Agency agencyno="6990">Infrastructure NSW</Agency><Date>2018-08-23</Date></Issued><Draft version="1"><Agency agencyno="10">Premier's Department</Agency><Date>2024-09-10</Date></Draft><Draft version="1"><Agency agencyno="7582">Cabinet Office</Agency><Date>2024-09-10</Date></Draft><Submitted><Officer>Shane Hamilton</Officer><Position>Acting Secretary</Position><Agency agencyno="10">Premier's Department</Agency><Date>2025-01-10</Date></Submitted><Submitted><Officer>Kate Boyd</Officer><Position>Secretary</Position><Agency agencyno="7582">Cabinet Office</Agency><Date>2025-01-10</Date></Submitted><Approved>2025-02-26</Approved><Issued><Agency agencyno="7582">Cabinet Office</Agency><Date>2025-03-11</Date></Issued><Issued><Agency agencyno="10">Premier's Department</Agency><Date>2025-03-11</Date></Issued></Status><LinkedTo type="SRNSW function">Government Administration</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">Public Sector Employment</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">Celebrations</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW function">Emergency Management</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW function">Infrastructure and Communications</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">State and Regional Development</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 2.1.1 - see GA28 10.3.1 no change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.2.6 - removed as covers a paper based approach to the distribution of Cabinet papers</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.2.3 - covered by NAP. Note added to 2.0.1</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.3.2 - removed as covered by NAP as duplicates</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 2.3.2 - see also GA28 GOVERNMENT RELATIONS - Advice 10.2.2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.1.1 - superseded by FA329 1.1.1 no change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.1.2 - superseded by FA329 1.1.2 no change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.3.1 - superdeded by FA329 1.2.1 no change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.1 - superseded by FA329 1.3.1 no change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.3 - superseded by FA329 1.3.1 no change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.2 - superseded by FA329 1.6.1 no change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.4 - superseded by GA28 19.16.1 and 2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.5 - superseded by FA329 1.3.3</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.6 - superseded by FA329 1.3.3</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.7 - see NAP</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.5.8 - superseded by FA329 1.3.3</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.6.1 - superseded by FA329 1.6.1</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.7.1 - superseded by FA329 1.7.1</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.7.2 - superseded by FA329 1.7.3</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.7.3 - superseded by FA329 1.4.2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.7.4 - superseded by FA329 1.6.2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.7.5 - superseded by FA329 1.4.4</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.7.6 - superseded by FA329 1.4.6</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.7.7 - superseded by FA329 1.4.7</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 9.2.3 - superseded by FA439 2.2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 9.2.4 - superseded by FA439 2.3</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 9.2.1 - superseded by FA439 1.1</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 9.2.2 - superseded by FA439 2.2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 9.1.1 - superseded by GA28 19.15.3</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 7.2.1 - see FA329 1.1.1</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.2.2 - Covered by NAP. These records are not held by Premier’s Department or The Cabinet Office</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.2.2 - see GDA13</LinkedTo><Comment author="SRNSW"><Paragraph>Entries 9.0.0 and 10.0.0 approved for use by Infrastructure NSW 23/8/2018 </Paragraph></Comment><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Public office (AR367)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph>The Department is the central policy agency for Government and is responsible for:<List><Item>the provision of support to the Premier, Cabinet, Ministers and agencies to integrate and coordinate policy and service delivery across government </Item><Item>coordination of the NSW State Plan and management of state-wide issues and projects</Item><Item>managing public sector staff and resources </Item><Item>review and reform of public sector performance </Item><Item>coordination and planning of State functions, official visits and events</Item><Item>coordination of legislative and parliamentary programs.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>The Department of Premier and Cabinet was created on 27 April 2007 by the combination of the former Premier's Department with the Cabinet Office. The Premier’s Department was initially established as a separate department of Government around 1909. Prior to this it existed as the Premier’s Office within the Department of Attorney-General and of Justice. The Cabinet Office has existed since around 1921, and has had various titles, including the Cabinet Section, the Cabinet and Parliamentary Division, and Cabinet Secretariat. It has always been associated with the Premier’s portfolio.</Paragraph><Source url="http://www.dpc.nsw.gov.au/home">Department of Premeir and Cabinet web site</Source><Source url="http://investigator.records.nsw.gov.au">State Records Control System</Source></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Functions (AR367)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph>This authority provides coverage for records relating to:<List><Item>the Aboriginal Trust Fund Repayment Scheme</Item><Item>the administration of grants and delivery or coordination of community support and assistance programs and projects </Item><Item>planning and coordination of major and special events, State functions and official visits</Item><Item>the management of honours and award programs</Item><Item>the provision of support to elected officials or office holders</Item><Item>planning and management of the public sector workforce</Item><Item>oversight and review of public sector performance</Item><Item>coordination and delivery of infrastructure projects</Item><Item>disaster, emergency and security threat response planning and coordination</Item><Item>the provision of policy advice to the Premier, Cabinet and departmental executive.</Item></List></Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Additional information (AR367)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph><Emphasis>Scope and coverage</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>This authority provides coverage for the core functional responsibilities and activities of the Department, namely those relating to:<List><Item>the provision of strategic advice and policy support services to the Premier and Government</Item><Item>the management of statewide issues, initiatives and projects</Item><Item>regulatory reform, performance reviews and service delivery improvement</Item><Item>management of public sector employee relations and workforce reforms</Item><Item>the provision of ministerial and parliamentary services to support the machinery of government </Item><Item>Government ceremonies and hospitality.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>The Department maintains records relating to these functions dating back to 1976 and potentially earlier. The authority will apply to permit the destruction of records dating from 1976 onwards. This date corresponds with the first Wran Ministry and in general with the date range of disposal recommendations previously authorised for use on an ongoing basis by the Department. Approved disposal actions for records identified as State archives may be applied irrespective of the date of the records. Authorisation for the destruction of records predating 1976 will be developed if required once any earlier records have been more comprehensively identified and appraised.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This authority is to be used in conjunction with <Source>Functional retention and disposal authority: cabinet secretariat, policy advice and support services </Source>(FA254, approved February 2008)) and with other current authorities covering records of specific ministerial portfolio responsibilities, such as local government, environment and heritage, assigned to the Premier. </Paragraph><Paragraph>This authority also includes coverage for the Aboriginal Trust Fund Repayment Scheme (ATFRS). The scheme was established in 2005 to repay to Aboriginal people and their descendants money that was collected from and put into trust accounts for them by the Aborigines Protection Board and later the Aborigines Welfare Board and was never repaid. </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Previous disposal authorisations</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>A number of disposal recommendations were previously issued to the Department. This functional retention and disposal authority will supersede these previous disposal recommendations, except where it may be appropriate to permit the discretionary transfer of records not covered by this authority as State archives under these earlier recommendations.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Consultation with external stakeholders</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Comments on the draft authority were received from:<List><Item>Emeritus Professor Mark Aronson, School of Law, University of NSW</Item><Item>Professor Lyn Carson, Centre for Citizenship and Public Policy, University of Western Sydney	</Item><Item>Dr Peter Tyler, Professional Historians Association</Item><Item>Professor Peter Read, Australian Research Council Professorial Fellow, University of Sydney.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>A summary of comments received and State Records' response is contained in the attachment to this report.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The following academics were also invited to review and comment on the authority but declined or did not respond:<List><Item>Dr Geoff Gallop, Professor and Director, Graduate School of Government, University of Sydney</Item><Item>Associate Professor Anne Junor, Deputy Director, Industrial Relations Research Centre, University of NSW</Item><Item>Professor Peter Anderson, Centre for Policing, Intelligence and Counter Terrorism, Macquarie University</Item><Item>Professor Allan McConnell, Leader, Department of Government and International Relations, Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences, University of Sydney</Item><Item>Honorary Professor James Guthrie, Discipline of Accounting, Economics and Business, University of Sydney</Item><Item>Associate Professor Michael Johnson, School of Social Sciences and International Studies, University of Sydney</Item><Item>Dr Geoffrey Hawker, Associate Professor, Politics and International Relations, Macquarie University</Item><Item>Associate Professor James Jose, Newcastle Business School, University of Newcastle.</Item></List></Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Justification (AR367)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph><Emphasis>Retention decisions</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Premier and Cabinet advised in its submission that the nominated minimum retention periods and disposal actions meet its current legal and statutory obligations and the administrative requirements of the organisation.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Records identified as State archives</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records identified as State archives include:<List><Item>records relating to the receipt and determination of claims made under the Aboriginal Trust Fund Repayment Scheme</Item><Item>guidelines and handbooks for board or committee appointments and standards of conduct </Item><Item>records of Community Cabinet meetings</Item><Item>registers or summary details of grant applications received by the organisation, records of committees or panels involved in the assessment of applications and records relating to the assessment and administration of applications where the grants are of State, local or regional significance, have broad impact or are approved by the Premier</Item><Item>records of policy, advice, projects and programs for the delivery or provision of services to support or assist the community</Item><Item>records relating to the formulation of policy, advice, plans and procedures for the management of emergencies and security threats, including liaison and meetings with community leaders and representatives concerning the management of security risks</Item><Item>records relating to responses to major security occurrences or to emergencies, natural disasters or incidents that have a significant impact on the State or a particular region or locality </Item><Item>records relating to incident response planning and coordination for major events</Item><Item>records relating to the development and review of codes of conduct for Ministers and ministerial staff and audits of Ministers' offices that identify major irregularities</Item><Item>records relating to the administration of awards and honours schemes and to the hosting of State ceremonies, festivities or celebrations, Royal visits and visits by foreign heads of State or leading dignitaries</Item><Item>records relating to the management of NSW emblems, the State flag and Coat of Arms</Item><Item>records of policy, procedures, awards and agreements governing public sector employees and employment conditions</Item><Item>records relating to the development of education and training programs for public-sector employees</Item><Item>records relating to the establishment and review of government agencies' structure, performance, programs and functions</Item><Item>reports relating to the profile of the public sector workforce and the status or outcomes of management or reform initiatives</Item><Item>records relating to the development and review of legislation and regulations</Item><Item>records relating to the management of key or State significant infrastructure projects</Item><Item>records relating to the registration of lobbyists</Item><Item>records relating to the issue of election writs for NSW State elections and by-elections and provision of advice to the Premier concerning the administration of casual Parliamentary vacancies</Item><Item>circulars and memoranda issued by the Premier/Department.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Records approved for destruction </Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records approved for destruction include records relating to:<List><Item>coordination of the administration of Aboriginal Trust Fund Repayment Scheme </Item><Item>the provision of assistance to government agencies concerning regulatory proposal development processes (advice relating to the content or nature of legislative or regulatory proposals is identified as State archives, entry 8.2.1 and 10.2.1)</Item><Item>security or emergency response planning where the agency does not play a lead or major role or has minimal input</Item><Item>emergency incidents that have a limited impact on persons or property, incident response exercises, and general liaison and information exchange with the community  </Item><Item>visits by representatives of other governments (visits by heads of State are identified as State archives, entry 6.5.1)</Item><Item>the coordination of arrangements for events, ceremonies, functions, exhibitions or displays, community meetings etc.</Item><Item>the provision of advice of a general nature concerning public sector employment matters and data collection for reporting purposes</Item><Item>the coordination of learning and development programs for public sector employees</Item><Item>infrastructure projects where the agency does not play a lead or major role or where the project is not of State significance</Item><Item>unsuccessful applications for and the administration of minor grant programs </Item><Item>notices and approvals of Ministerial absences, routine audits of Ministers' offices (audits identifying irregularities leading to findings of misuse or inappropriate practices are identified as State archives, entry 5.1.1), and arrangements for the security and protection of current and former office holders</Item><Item>advice and approvals of requests for the use of State symbols</Item><Item>routine liaison activities and information exchange undertaken with Commonwealth, State and/or local government organisations in order to assist in the coordination of government administration or projects</Item><Item>reference documentation and reports received for information purposes requiring no further action</Item><Item>the receipt of notifications from the Legislative Assembly relating to the administration of casual vacancies (records relating to the issue of election writs for State elections and by-elections and provision of advice to the Premier concerning the administration of casual Parliamentary vacancies are identified as State archives, entry 10.1.1 and 10.1.2)</Item><Item>the registration of interest by members of the public to serve on boards and committees</Item><Item>Cabinet Office set of agenda and minutes of Executive Council meetings (approval for destruction is subject to transfer of the Governor's Office set as State archives).</Item></List></Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Attachment: report on external consultation (AR367)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph><Emphasis>Background</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>The following provides a summary of comments received from Emeritus Professor Mark Aronson, Professor Lyn Carson, Professor Peter Read and Dr Peter Tyler on the draft retention and disposal authority for the records of the Department of Premier and Cabinet.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>General comments</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Professor Carson limited her feedback to the function of Community Cabinets, and endorsed the retention of these records as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Dr Read made a general comment on the classes relating to the Aboriginal Trust Fund Repayment Scheme records: 'I came to the task in some trepidation, but on the Aboriginal part, which is my area of expertise, I was pleasantly surprised to see that the papers marked for disposal seemed a perfectly reasonable choice. So I have no problem with the recommendations for this section'.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Dr Tyler commented 'as a practising professional historian, I naturally have an inclination towards preserving all official records, especially those of an agency which is so central to the functioning of the State of New South Wales. At the same time, I recognise that this is not a realistic or practical objective. Under the circumstances, I believe that you have made a cautious and prudent assessment of the potential future administrative or historical value of the documents described in the draft'. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Professor Aronson commented 'I am struck by how much thought and care have gone into its preparation'.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Dr Tyler and Professor Aronson also provided comments and recommendations in relation to a number of specific entries. Details of their comments and any amendment of the authority in response are outlined below: </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Note</Emphasis>: The comments of external stakeholders relate to a previous version of the draft authority. All amendments outlined in State Records' response have been incorporated into this version of the authority.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 1.1.3 </Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>ABORIGINAL TRUST FUND REPAYMENT SCHEME (AFTRS) – Claims</Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to meetings and liaison held with other agencies and stakeholders to coordinate and discuss the administration of claims processes. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Dr Tyler</Paragraph><Paragraph>This is a somewhat contentious area, which is likely to be of ongoing historic interest.  I consider that 10 years before disposal is too brief, and would suggest a minimum of 30 years, perhaps even 50 years.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>I would strongly counsel against destruction after 10 years. It is entirely possible that information relevant to classes 1.1.1 and 1.1.2 will be overlooked, buried as it will sometimes be within documents regarding meetings and liaison. It is much safer to retain these documents, rather than rely on the accuracy of the sorting process.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Dr Tyler's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention for 30 or 50 years is considered overly long, especially given the records relate to coordination of the administration of the scheme, not to its establishment or the determination of eligibility of claimants. However the records may be a useful reference if other schemes need to be established in the future, therefore an increase in the retention period from 10 to 20 years after action completed is supported. This equates to the proposed retention period for records covered by entry 8.2.5, which also deal with the administration of processes and procedures. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Professor Aronson's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>The records covered by 1.1.1 (records relating to receipt and determination of claims) would be maintained separately to records covered by 1.1.3. It is unlikely that records coming under 1.1.3, which relate to coordination between agencies of the administration of the scheme and the claims handling process, would contain information relevant to the determination of a particular individual's claim. </Paragraph><Paragraph>There is the possibility that records covered by 1.1.3 may be overlap with records covered by 1.1.2 with respect to consultation on the development of guidelines, in which case the application of 1.1.2 to the records should prevail.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Details of amendment</Emphasis>: Retention period increased from proposed minimum of 10 to 20 years after action completed.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 3.1.4</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>COMMUNITY SUPPORT – Committees</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of guidelines, handbooks and information resources, brochures, etc. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Dr Tyler </Paragraph><Paragraph>I favour these being retained for a minimum of 10 years after action completed. This would cover the period of two State elections (and possible changes of Government), and would help to ensure that corporate memory is preserved through a period in which there might be substantial organisational changes.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>There should be a carve-out from 3.1.4 for anything to do with indigenous affairs. These records will be necessary to assess the provenance of policy and guidelines. Historians will otherwise be left with an archive of government policy, but with the occasional question mark about the extent to which it might have been developed in response to external representations.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Dr Tyler's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Recommendation adopted.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Professor Aronson's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of the policy (e.g. to increase and foster opportunities for the community (or particular community groups) to participate in decision making through representation on boards and committees) are identified for retention as State archives under entry 3.4.1 (Policy). These records would capture records of consultations or representations influencing policy development.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The guidelines and handbooks developed by DPC primarily deal with procedural processes to be observed by agencies to give effect to established government policy. The records intended to be covered by this entry would primarily relate to the compilation and drafting of these documents, not the formulation of government policy. </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Details of amendments</Emphasis>:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Entry 3.1.4 amended to increase nominated minimum retention period for records relating to the compilation and drafting of guidelines and handbooks for managing appointments, remuneration and standards of conduct for board and committee members from proposed 5 to 10 years.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Additional entry, 3.1.5, included to separately cover brochures and web site information produced for the public.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entries 3.3.3 and 3.3.4</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>COMMUNITY SUPPORT - Grant assistance</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to the assessment and administration of grants that are not of State, local or regional significance, do not have broad impact or are not approved by the Premier and grant applications that are unsuccessful. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>I would be interested to know whether political scientists would prefer that documents in 3.3.3 and 3.3.4 be retained as State archives. Minor grants have always been a potent political tool, even though considered individually, they lack any broader impact.</Paragraph><Paragraph>To adopt recommendations re 3.3.3 and 3.3.4 would entail retention of all records relating to the receipt, assessment and administration of grant applications as State archives. However retention of records that would provide an insight into grants of a minor nature or of applications which were  not successful has been incorporated into the authority. Details of any grants or funding disbursed by the Department are also recorded in the Department's annual report.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Details of amendments</Emphasis>: </Paragraph><Paragraph>Wording of entry 3.3.1 amended to explicitly include reference to unsuccessful grant applications. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Additional entry included to identify records of committees or panels involved in the assessment of grant or funding applications as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entries 4.2.1 and 4.2.2 </Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT – Community Liaison</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>These entries covered records of liaison and meetings with community leaders and representatives of community groups to discuss matters or issues relating to the management or minimisation of security risks. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Records of liaison and meetings with community leaders and representatives of 'high risk' groups were identified as State archives (4.2.1). Records of meeting and liaison with other groups to discuss security or emergency management were approved for destruction (4.2.2).</Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>I am unsure of the exact difference between 4.2.1 and 4.2.2. On my reading of the draft, 'high risk' groups have no carve-outs from State archives, whilst others do. However, a group’s risk level is not necessarily stable over long periods of time. It would therefore be preferable for 4.2.2 to be State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>To minimise application of subjective criteria and clarify distinction between nature and types of processes and interaction covered the entries have been amended as follows:</Paragraph><Paragraph>4.2.1 Records of liaison and meetings with leaders and representatives of community groups to discuss matters or issues relating to the management or minimisation of security risks.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Required as State archives</Paragraph><Paragraph>4.2.2 Records relating to general liaison and information exchange with community groups concerning security or emergency management arrangements or initiatives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Retain minimum of 5 years after action completed, then destroy</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 4.3.2</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT – Emergency and disaster response</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to the response to emergency incidents that have a limited impact on persons or property (i.e. do not involve significant loss of life or major injury or damage to property within the State or a particular region or locality or do not have major policy/legislative impact). Includes pro-active response during major events that are incident free or where incidents are minor such as World Youth Day and Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC). </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Dr Tyler</Paragraph><Paragraph>Despite their 'limited impact' in the immediate sense, such events can have an enduring interest and historic value (e.g. the Springbok Rugby tour of 1971). I would favour these documents being retained as State Records.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>As it stands, 4.3.2 allows for the eventual destruction of records of proactive crisis management where a major crisis was averted. That is in contrast to 4.3.1 which rightly seeks to archive the records relating to major incidents that have occurred. We surely have something to learn, however, from crisis management that successfully averted crises. I am not wholly against 4.3.2. Rather, I suggest that it be amended, so that documents are retained as State archives where they relate to crisis management for major events, even though they turned out to be incident-free.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Dr Tyler's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>DPC is generally not the primary coordinating, planning or management agency with respect to this function and has limited involvement with respect to incidents of minor impact. Records of the Police or Emergency Services agencies would be the primary source records for this type of research.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Professor Aronson's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Recommendation adopted.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Details of amendments:</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Scope of entry 4.3.2 amended to limit application to records relating to responses to emergency incidents that have a limited impact on persons or property.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Additional entry included identifying records relating to pro-active incident, emergency or crisis response coordination and planning for major events (such as World Youth Day and Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC)) as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 4.3.3</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT – Emergency and disaster response</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to routine correspondence, enquiries and provision of routine information about emergency arrangements. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>If the recommendation at 4.3.3 is designed in part to preserve evidence negating negligence allegations, then it will need to be kept longer than 7 years. The standard limitation deadlines for negligence actions can be considerably longer for those who were children at the time of the event. </Paragraph><Paragraph>To encompass limitations periods for those who were children at the time of the incident would require increasing the retention period to a minimum of 25 years after action completed.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Details of amendments:</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>After further consultation with Department justification amended as records unlikely to be required for legal action arising from an incident.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 4.4.1</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT – Exercises &amp; training</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to the conduct of the exercises to test preparedness for emergencies or security incidents. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Dr Tyler</Paragraph><Paragraph>Such exercises might take place less frequently than [proposed] 5 years.  I think a minimum of 7 years would be preferable.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Recommendation adopted</Emphasis>. Retention period increased from 5 to minimum of 7 years after action completed.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 4.7.2</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT – Planning</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to the formulation and development of plans and strategic initiatives for emergency, security or disaster preparedness and response within the State where the agency has no or only minor input into planning processes. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Dr Tyler</Paragraph><Paragraph>Such exercises might take place less frequently than 5 years. I think a minimum of 7 years would be preferable.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>I would agree with 4.7.2 only if the same records are to be retained as State archives by the agency or agencies with more input.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Dr Tyler's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>DPC is generally not the primary coordinating, planning or management agency with respect to the development of these types of plans or strategies and this entry covers circumstances where the agency has no or only minor input into planning processes. However, increase in retention from 5 to 7 years is supported.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Re Professor Aronson's comments:</Paragraph><Paragraph>DPC is generally not the primary coordinating, planning or management agency with respect to the development of these types of plans or strategies. Records are identified as State archives under NSW Police authority (DA220, 6.6.2, 6.9.1 and 6.9.2) and NSW Health authority (DA25, 27.1.1 – 27.1.4). Planning by Emergency Services will similarly be retained as State archives when disposal authorisation is developed for the State Emergency Services and Emergency Management NSW.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Details of amendments:</Emphasis> Retention period increased from 5 to minimum of 7 years after action completed.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 5.4.2 </Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>MINISTERIAL AND PARLIAMENTARY SERVICES – Security (includes Ministerial protection)</Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to liaison activities and reports concerning security and protection for current and former office holders or their families where there was no security occurrence or the security occurrence was of a non threatening nature (e.g. a false alarm). </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>I agree that the documents need not be kept forever, but I do think that [the proposed] 3 years is too short a minimum retention period. Minor harassment incidents from a single source can fester for some time before they become major in character.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Recommendation adopted.</Emphasis> Retention period increased from 3 to 7 years. 7 year retention period is consistent with periods applying to records relating to minor security breaches or incidents in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records</Source> (GA28, 16.24.3).</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 8.2.7</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>PUBLIC SECTOR PERFORMANCE REVIEW - Regulation review and reform</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to research undertaken in support of regulation review activities. Records include literature searches, statistics, surveys and other raw data. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Dr Tyler</Paragraph><Paragraph>For the reasons given in 7.7.6 [i.e. Records may be required for reference and reuse and to verify information provided in final reports], I consider that the raw data should be retained as State Records.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>The research records underpinning regulation review activities should be retained as State archives. There are large debates within the academic research communities about the design, efficacy and quality of the regulation review procedures and outcomes, and the documents at 8.2.7 will be a valuable resource for future research within those debates.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Recommendations adopted.</Emphasis> Disposal class amended to identify records of statistics, surveys and other raw data collected or collated for the purposes of regulatory review or reform projects as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 10.1.2</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>STRATEGIC POLICY AND ADVICE - Legal Policy</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating the provision of advice on the administration of casual vacancies for the NSW Parliament. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>I am unsure of the reasoning behind the recommendation at 10.1.2. It seems to be that the important documents will come from the Assembly. However, the Premier needs the confidence of the Legislative Assembly, and it is therefore conceivable that important documents relating to the administration of casual vacancies could at some time have originated (or will originate) in the DPC.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Legislative Assembly vacancies are filled though by-elections which are administered/arranged through the Legislative Assembly. The DPC does not usually prepare any documents in relation to this process but receives advice from the Legislative Assembly of the proposed election timetable and return of the writs. Records relating to the issue of election writs are identified as State archives under entry 10.1.1.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Details of amendments:</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Based on further advice from and consultation with DPC this entry has been amended to clarify its scope applies to records relating to the provision of advice to the Premier concerning the administration of casual vacancies with the Parliament and these records are identified as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>An additional entry, 10.1.3, has been included to cover records relating to the receipt of advice from the Legislative Assembly on timetables and the return of writs for the administration of casual vacancies. These records have a proposed minimum retention period of 5 years after action completed.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Entry 10.5.2</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>STRATEGIC POLICY AND ADVICE – Reporting</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records relating to reports received from agencies of government and non-Government organisations for the purpose of keeping the Premier's office informed of their activities where issues dealt with in the reports require no further action from the Premier's Office. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Comment from Professor Aronson</Paragraph><Paragraph>I understand the recommendation at 10.5.2, but suggest that the minimum retention period might be too short. Further action from the Premier’s Office might be needed beyond the 2 year period, even though it is appeared at first that the matter was closed. I therefore suggest a slightly longer retention period.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Recommendation adopted.</Emphasis> Retention period increased from 2 to minimum of 5 years after action completed.</Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Public office (AR416)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph>The Department of Premier and Cabinet is the central policy agency for Government and is responsible for:<List><Item>the provision of support to the Premier, Cabinet, Ministers and agencies to integrate and coordinate policy and service delivery across government </Item><Item>coordination and management of state-wide planning, issues and projects </Item><Item>review and reform of public sector performance </Item><Item>coordination and planning of State functions, official visits and events</Item><Item>coordination of legislative and parliamentary programs.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>The Department of Premier and Cabinet was created in 2007 by the combination of the Premier's Department with the Cabinet Office. The Premier’s Department was initially established around 1909 and the Cabinet Office, which has always been associated with the Premier’s portfolio, has existed since 1921.</Paragraph><Source url="www.dpc.nsw.gov.au">Department of Premeir and Cabinet web site</Source><Source>Appraisal report AR367</Source></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Functions (AR416)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph>This authority provides coverage for records relating to the administration of grants for community services, programs and projects.</Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Additional information (AR416)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph>This authority is a revision of the current retention and disposal requirements applying to records of grant programs delivered by the Department of Premier and Cabinet (DPC) under functional retention and disposal authority FA313 (approved October 2011). </Paragraph><Paragraph>DPC, in the past and currently, provides grants to local councils, non-government organisations, community groups and (in limited circumstances) individuals to undertake various community projects, activities or services. The grant programs generally involve the provision of small amounts of money only for community based local projects or activities. In most instances the NSW Government's contribution will only be a proportion of the total cost of the project or activity which they fund. These programs may be directly administered by DPC or by other agencies on behalf of DPC, for example the Community Building Partnership program, a DPC funded program implemented via a joint arrangement between DPC and the Office of Communities. The disbursement of funds to successful grant applicants under these programs, while administered by another agency, is still approved by the Premier as the responsible minister and subject to DPC oversight and monitoring. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Currently under FA313, records relating to the administration of approved grants, where these are of local significance or are approved by the Premier, are identified for retention as State archives. It has since been identified that, because of the nature of the grants and funding programs generally administered by DPC (or by other agencies on behalf of DPC), use of the Premier's approval or a project being of local significance as a criteria for identification of State archives will result in the retention of the majority of all records relating to the administration of successful grants as State archives. This is not considered warranted given the types of projects or activities receiving funding and the availability of summary information about grant applicants, successful recipients, types of projects funded and the amounts provided in other records being retained as State archives.  </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Changes to reduce over retention</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>This authority modifies the criteria for records requiring retention as State archives and reduces the current minimum retention requirements applying to records of unsuccessful grant applications.  </Paragraph><Paragraph>The amendments include:<List><Item>modification of the entry covering records of assessment committees or panels decisions with respect to the disbursement of grants and funding to include 'submissions to the Premier or responsible delegated officer concerning recommendations for grant or funding approvals and records documenting the Premier's or delegated officer's approval or variance of these recommendations' (1.1).</Item><Item>modification of the current criteria for identification of records relating to the administration of successful applications warranting retention as State archives under FA313, entry 3.3.2 from 'grants [that] are of State, local or regional significance, have broad impact or are approved by the Premier' to '[grants that relate] to projects or services of State or regional significance' (1.4). Records documenting the provision of grants for services, projects or programs of State or regional significance are still identified as State archives. This would generally apply to major programs through which the Government provides funding to non government organisations and local government councils to deliver essential frontline services to the community.</Item><Item>a reduction in the current minimum retention requirements applying to records of unsuccessful grant applications from 7 years to 2 years. The amended retention period is sufficient to support accountability with respect to assessment processes. Details of grants or funding disbursed by an agency are documented in their Annual report. Summary records documenting the receipt and assessment of applications and recommendations and approvals concerning the allocation of funds are identified as State archives (1.6).</Item><Item>inclusion of an additional class permitting the destruction of summary records or registers of grant applications (successful or unsuccessful) where the information or details will also be documented in the organisation’s annual report or related assessment committee records or ministerial submissions. This will enable the destruction of records where the information is otherwise duplicated or available from other records being retained as State archives (1.3).</Item></List></Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Justification (AR416)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph><Emphasis>Retention decisions</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>The Department of Premier and Cabinet has confirmed in its submission that the nominated minimum retention periods and disposal actions in the authority are appropriate and meet the current legal and statutory obligations and administrative requirements of the organisation. They will also ensure consistent outcomes with respect to the retention of records where the programs are administered by other agencies on behalf of the Department.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The proposed amendments, while limiting the criteria for identification of case records to be retained as State archives, provides more detailed guidance with respect to records of application assessment and approval processes required to be retained as State archives and also permits the destruction of duplicate information rather than requiring this also to be retained as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Records identified as State archives</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records identified as State archives document:<List><Item>decisions and approvals with respect to the disbursement or allocation of grant funding to support various community projects or initiatives. This includes summary records or registers of grant applications (successful and unsuccessful) where the information or detail is not otherwise documented in the organisation’s annual report, committee or panel records or ministerial submissions.</Item><Item>records of successful grant applications and their administration where the grant relates to support for service delivery programs of State or regional significance.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Records identified for destruction</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records identified for eventual destruction include records relating to:<List><Item>summary records or registers of grant applications where the information or details are also documented in the organisation’s annual report, committee or panel records or ministerial submissions</Item><Item>records relating to the administration of grants to support the provision or delivery of local community projects or services</Item><Item>records relating to the assessment of grant applications that are unsuccessful.</Item></List></Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Background (AR573)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph>The Premier’s Department was initially established around 1909 and The Cabinet Office has existed since 1921.Currently they are separate entities although the Premier’s Department manages The Cabinet Office’s records.</Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Context type="appraisal report"><ContextTitle>Issue (AR573)</ContextTitle><ContextContent><Paragraph>The Cabinet Office and the Premier’s Department use FA254 (issued 2008) and FA313 (revised in 2018) for their records.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Premier’s Department recently reviewed the disposal authorities and approached State Records NSW to request minor updates (e.g. change of wording from Cabinet minutes to Cabinet meeting submissions in entry 2). As part of the review State Records NSW suggested:<List><Item>changes to the retention periods grants records</Item><Item>moving entries from FA254 into FA313 so they would have a single disposal authority.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>This was agreed to.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The following changes are proposed:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Records	Change	Justification	Entry</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Cabinet Office’s set of agenda and Executive Council minutes.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Retain until administrative or reference use ceases then destroy	Removal of requirement that The Cabinet Office can only destroy their set of  Executive Council Minutes once it is confirmed that the Office of the Governor has  transferred their set as State archives.	The Office of the Governor manages the hard copy signed set of Executive Council Minutes and has already transferred up to 2007 to the State Archives Collection. The more recent sets are held securely at Government House. It is not considered necessary for Cabinet to retain copies until they are transferred.	1</Paragraph><Paragraph>Cabinet and community Cabinet papers</Paragraph><Paragraph>Required as State archives	No change. Previously these records were covered in FA254 and have been moved into FA313. 	To simplify disposal.	2 &amp; 3</Paragraph><Paragraph>Summary records of unsuccessful and successful community grants.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Required as State archives	Previously summary records were only required as State archives where the information or detail was not otherwise documented in the organisation’s annual report, committee or panel records or ministerial submissions.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This has been changed so that summary records of grants are required as State archives regardless of mentions in annual reports, committee records or panel reports.	Details in annual reports can be minimal and access to information about grants will be facilitated by having the information in one place rather than in committee or panel records. There is public interest in grants awarded by the Premier after a recent ICAC investigation found corrupt conduct by a former Premier in connection with grant funding. </Paragraph><Paragraph>The Cabinet Office now requires this type of summary record to be created in the Grants Administration Guide.	4</Paragraph><Paragraph>Final reports of the outcomes of projects funded by grants. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Required as State archives.	A gap in coverage was identified.	These reports will record details of the grants process and how public money was spent. 	4</Paragraph><Paragraph>Successful grant applications.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Retain minimum of 7 years after all grant conditions are complete	Previously successful grant applications for projects or services of State or regional significance were required as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This has been removed so that all successful grant applications are retained for 7 years after the project is finalised. 	Grant applications tend to be operational records and the records of successful grants being retained as State archives under entry 4 (deliberations and decisions of committees or panels, submissions to the Premier, Premier’s approval, summary records of grants, and reports of outcomes)  meet State archives’ needs.	5</Paragraph><Paragraph>Unsuccessful grant applications.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Retain minimum of 7 years after action completed, then destroy	Retention period increased from 4 to 7 years.	To allow for auditing of records which can take place up to 6 years after decision not to approve application.	6</Paragraph><Paragraph>Benchmarking</Paragraph><Paragraph>The authority has been benchmarked against:<List><Item>Victoria: Department of Premier and Cabinet (2024)</Item><Item>South Australia: Department of Premier and Cabinet (2021)</Item><Item>Queensland: Department of the Premier and Cabinet (2012)</Item><Item>Tasmania: Department of Premier and Cabinet (2007)</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Consultation</Paragraph><Paragraph>State Records NSW consulted with the following:<List><Item>The Audit Office of NSW: the Acting Assistant Auditor-General - Performance Audit  consulted with staff who have worked on audits of grants administration in the past and they have noted that they have not faced any issues previously where they have been unable to access grants administration records because they weren’t retained for a long enough period. </Item><Item>The Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC): no response received. </Item><Item>Museums of History NSW supported the changes. </Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Shane Hamilton, Acting Secretary, Premier’s Department, and Kate Boyd, Secretary, The Cabinet Office, advised in the submission that the nominated minimum retention periods and disposal actions meet current legal and statutory obligations and the administrative requirements of the organisation.</Paragraph><Paragraph>FA254 will be superseded.  </Paragraph></ContextContent></Context><Term type="function" itemno="1.0.0"><TermTitle>ABORIGINAL TRUST FUND REPAYMENT SCHEME (AFTRS)</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The administration of the Aboriginal Trust Fund Repayment Scheme (ATFRS) established to repay to Aboriginal people and their descendants money that was put into trust funds and never repaid.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Term type="activity" itemno="1.1.0"><TermTitle>Claims</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The receipt and assessment of claims.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="1.1.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to applications made under the Aboriginal Trust Fund Repayment Scheme. Records include:<List><Item>the register of the applications</Item><Item>applications and supporting evidence </Item><Item>correspondence with applicants</Item><Item>research into, assessments of and recommendations on applications (this includes recommendations of the AFTRS unit and of the AFTRS Panel or the DG to the Minister in respect of the claim)</Item><Item>final determinations and advice to applicants regarding recommendations/decisions</Item><Item>appeals by applicants and their determination.</Item></List></Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document individual case management where the government had far-reaching impact on the lives of individuals within the community.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="index">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="1.1.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of guidelines governing the making and payment of claims. Records include background research, draft versions containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation with stakeholders, etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document how claims are to be assessed and determined and provide context for the decisions made with respect to individual claims.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="1.1.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to meetings and liaison held with other agencies and stakeholders to coordinate and discuss the administration of claims processes. Includes meetings with NSW State Records, Legal Aid, Aboriginal Affairs, Department of Community Services etc. Records include agenda and minutes of meetings, correspondence relating to actions or business arising.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">20</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports use of records for reference with respect to arrangements for administration of the scheme. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period increased from minimum of 10 years to 20 years in response to comments received from external consultation recommending longer term retention in case similar schemes need to be established in the future.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term></Term><Term type="function" update="2024-09-04" itemno="2.0.0"><TermTitle>CABINET SERVICES</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The provision of administrative services to Cabinet and its committees and to the Executive Council.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef><ItemNoRef>1.0.2</ItemNoRef><SeeText>for records relating to meetings of National Cabinet.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to administrative arrangements for meetings.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advice</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the provision of advice to the Premier, Ministers or other government organisations.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>LEGAL SERVICES</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advice</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to internal or external legal advice.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to policies, procedures and strategic planning.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>TECHNOLOGY &amp; TELECOMMUNICATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Application development and management</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to audit trails of eCabinet showing access logs.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GDA">13</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Records of a Minister's office</AuthorityTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the development and finalisation of Cabinet submissions and Bills as created or modified by the Minister’s office</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GDA">13</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Records of a Minister's office</AuthorityTitleRef><SeeText>for individual Minister’s copies of Cabinet minutes and papers containing briefing notes and departmental advices.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Comment author="P&amp;C"><Paragraph>Terminology has changed – now called ‘Cabinet Submissions’, not ‘Cabinet Minutes’.</Paragraph></Comment><Class itemno="2.0.1" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>The Cabinet Office’s set of agenda and Executive Council Minutes. </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Note:</Emphasis> the Office of the Governor retains the original  copy of Executive Council Minutes signed by the Governor. A copy of the Executive Council Minute and the attached business papers are returned to the originating Department, which is responsible for transferring the papers as State archives under the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records</Source> GOVERNMENT RELATIONS - Submissions.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalTrigger>administrative or reference use ceases</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2011.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark:<List><Item>Consistent with Queensland and South Australia</Item><Item>Victoria retains duplicate copies of minutes and agendas until action completed.</Item><Item>Tasmania retains for 2 years after action completed.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change except for removal of requirement for The Cabinet Office to confirm that the Office of the Governor’s set of Executive Council Minutes has been transferred as State archives before destruction can take place. </Paragraph><Paragraph>The Office of the Governor manages the original set of agenda and Executive Council Minutes that are signed by the Governor and has transferred up to 2007 to the State Archives Collection. The more recent sets are held securely at Government House. It is not considered necessary for Cabinet to retain copies until they are transferred as State archives as Museums of History NSW or the Office of the Governor holds the primary record.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A hardcopy Executive Council Minute is prepared according to a Cabinet template and must not exceed one page. It includes the subject, name of the Department, document number, the signature of the relevant Minister and the Governor.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The copy of the Executive Council Minutes and attached business papers are returned to the Department and are required as State archives under the General retention and disposal authority: administrative records GOVERNMENT RELATIONS - Submissions. The set maintained by the Departments will include additional records relating to the preparation and implementation of the decisions.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 2.0.1 - No change</LinkedTo><Comment author="agency"><Paragraph>Executive Council minutes</Paragraph><Paragraph>Matters are placed before the Executive Council in the form of minutes conveying recommendations from Ministers.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Each minute is accompanied by an explanatory note outlining the background or purpose of the minute.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Executive Council minute templates (DOCX 86.14KB) must be used. Please refer to the Guidelines for Executive Council Minutes (PDF 1.39MB) for directions on filling out the templates and requirements for Explanatory Notes and other attachments.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In eCabinet, the Executive Council Minute should be lodged as a submission with all other relevant documentation as attachments.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Executive Council minutes are not Cabinet documents.</Paragraph></Comment><Comment author="agency"><Paragraph>Executive Council minute and attachments must be lodged no later than midday on the Friday before the Executive Council meeting (which is usually held each Wednesday). Exemptions should only be sought (through Cabinet Secretariat) in exceptional circumstances where urgent consideration of the minute is necessary.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Each minute is reviewed by The Cabinet Office and then the matter is listed on the Executive Council agenda by the Governor's Official Secretary. Minutes will only be put forward if the matter has received any necessary Cabinet approval, and compliance with the NSW Government Guide to Better Regulationlaunch and the Subordinate Legislation Act 1989launch has been documented.</Paragraph></Comment><Comment author="agency"><Paragraph>After the meeting, the relevant minister is notified of the decision. The minister's office or relevant agency can then make any necessary administrative arrangements in relation to the decision, for example publication of legislation on the NSW Legislation website or notification of a matter through the Government Gazette.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Matters put forward to the Executive Council must remain confidential until they have been approved. While it is convention that the Governor should only act on the advice of ministers, the Governor may seek further information or, in exceptional circumstances, dissent from this advice.</Paragraph></Comment><Comment author="P&amp;C"><Paragraph>Expand title to ‘Executive Council’, delete ‘This includes schedules of agenda items prepared by the Cabinet Secretariat’ and rephrase to ‘copies of agenda prepared by…’ (instead of ‘copies of agenda items’).</Paragraph></Comment><Comment author="SRNSW"><Paragraph>Amended description based on comments from P&amp;C</Paragraph></Comment><Comment author="SRNSW"><Paragraph>The provision of administrative services to the Executive Council.</Paragraph></Comment><Comment author="SRNSW"><Paragraph>Matters are placed before the Executive Council in the form of minutes conveying recommendations from Ministers. Minutes are forwarded by Ministers to the Cabinet Secretariat and then forwarded to the Official Secretary to the Governor. The agenda paper of recommendations for consideration is prepared by the Official Secretary. At the meeting, when the Councillors have signified their concurrence in the matters before them the agenda papers are so endorsed by the Governor. The approved Minutes are signed by the Governor and Clerk of the Council and returned to the Office of the originating Minister.</Paragraph></Comment></Class><Class itemno="2.0.2" update="2026-01-10"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Key records of Cabinet and Cabinet committees. Includes:<List><Item>Official set of Cabinet and Cabinet committee meeting submissions and papers</Item><Item>Registers of Cabinet decisions and meeting attendance</Item><Item>Register of Cabinet Submissions including Cabinet Submission Number, subject, matter, minister, meeting date, date received and resolutions</Item><Item>Cabinet Minutes which have been withdrawn before being considered by Cabinet, including correspondence dealing with the Minutes and their withdrawal and supporting documentation.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>Note:</Emphasis> individual Ministers copies of Cabinet papers can be destroyed under the Normal Administrative Practice provisions of the <Source url="http://www.bogus.com">State Records Regulation</Source>  as duplicates.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 1. Provides evidence of the deliberations and decisions of the NSW Government and provides evidence of the deliberations of the NSW Government and the reasoning behind decisions not to refer matters to Cabinet.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Precedent: Consistent with Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Benchmark: Consistent with Victoria, Queensland, South Australia and Victoria.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 1. Provides evidence of the deliberations and decisions of the NSW Government.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Consistent with Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark: Consistent with Victoria, Queensland, South Australia and Victoria.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/remarks: No change. Previously these records were covered in FA254 and have been moved into FA313 to simplify disposal.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.2.1 - No change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.2.4 - No change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.2.5 - No change</LinkedTo><Comment author="P&amp;C"><Paragraph>The team does not keep records of the ‘formal development of Cabinet and Cabinet Committee meeting agenda’. The development of agenda is an iterative, administrative process, and any records produced are ephemeral and facilitative and should be covered by class 1.5. The final agenda is the key record.</Paragraph></Comment></Class></Term><Term type="function" itemno="3.0.0"><TermTitle>COMMUNITY SUPPORT</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of facilitating, delivering or coordinating programs or projects to assist or support or to address issues impacting on the general community or targeted community groups such as regional or rural communities, the Aboriginal community, women, seniors, children, etc. </Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records of addresses, speeches, media releases or statements delivered or issued by the Premier.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GDA">13</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Records of a Minister's office</AuthorityTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to Ministerial involvements in grants and funding decisions.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Term type="activity" itemno="3.1.0"><TermTitle>Committees</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with the management of executive and advisory committees and task forces.  </Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>LEGAL SERVICES</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advice</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to legal advice furnished to committees</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="3.1.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the registration of persons interested in serving on boards and committees. Records include expressions of interest, applications, correspondence with applicants.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalTrigger>interest withdrawn or reference use ceases</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records retained for administrative purposes to facilitate the identification of persons interested in and with relevant qualifications for participating in Boards and Committees. Records do not document the selection or appointment process. Records relating to the establishment and appointment of persons to a Board or Committee are covered by the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records</Source>.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="3.1.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to advertisements on behalf of agencies seeking candidates to sit on boards and committees. Records include requests from agencies, and the placement of advertisements.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">2</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records only needed to serve immediate administrative processes which once completed will only require reference for a short period. Retention period is consistent with records relating to the coordination of the placement of job advertisements in FA294 covering records of government advertising (1.2.1 and 1.2.2). Agencies are responsible for management or administration of appointment processes.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="3.1.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Guidelines and handbooks relating to board or committee appointments, remuneration, standards of conduct, etc. This includes guidelines and handbooks developed for use by agencies or for board or committee members.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the nature of people’s interaction with government. Guidelines and handbooks developed by the Department for use by agencies primarily address and outline procedural processes to be observed in the management of appointments and expected standards of conduct of appointed board or committee members. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Entries 3.1.3 - 3.1.5 redrafted to clarify scope of coverage in response to comments received from external consultation.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.1.4"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of guidelines and handbooks concerning board or committee appointments, remuneration, standards of conduct, etc. Includes records of drafting and development processes.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">10</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for ongoing administrative or reference purposes. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period increased from 5 to 10 years in response to comments received from external consultation recommending increased retention to encompass period of 2 State election cycles to support retention of corporate memory across potential government or organisational change.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Guidelines and handbooks developed by the Department for use by agencies primarily address and outline procedural processes to be observed in the management of appointments and expected standards of conduct of appointed board or committee members. The records covered by this entry would document development and compilation of content of these published resources. Records documenting the development of government policy (e.g. to increase or foster opportunities for the community, or particular groups within the community, to participate in government decision-making through representation on government boards and committees) are identified for retention as State archives under 3.4.1 below (COMMUNITY SUPPORT - Policy). Records under 3.4.1 would capture and document records of consultation or representations influencing the development of policy.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="3.1.5"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Summary information resources and brochures developed for the public relating to or promoting community representation on boards and committees.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>superseded or withdrawn</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records are produced for general information purposes and contain brief summary information only. Retention period supports potential reference use for review or redevelopment of resources.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="3.2.0" update="2025-02-27"><TermTitle>Community Cabinets</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Activities associated with arranging and responding to issues arising from Community Cabinets. Includes arrangements for Cabinet visits to regional and suburban centres to hold formal Cabinet meetings and Ministerial meetings with local organisations and community groups.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="3.2.1" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to regional meetings of Cabinet and forums or meetings held as part of regional visits, e.g. correspondence regarding arrangements, invitations and visits to local areas of interest or concern, submissions from local organisations or Local Government, advice from relevant Minister on submissions, local initiatives, records documenting issues raised or matters discussed during meetings, forums and Q&amp;A sessions and briefings and reports relating to the investigation of issues raised.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 3. Records document the nature of people’s interaction with government and its influence on the administration of government.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008 and 2011.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark:<List><Item>Queensland retains Community Cabinet proceedings as State archives and invitations to submit deputations are retained for 5 years after last action.</Item><Item>Victoria retains the facilitation of Cabinet meetings held in the community for 7 years after last action.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Combination of 2 entries from FA313 and FA254 into 1 entry.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 3.2.1 - No change</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.3.1 - No change</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.2.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to arrangements for community cabinets. Includes advertising and notification of meetings, booking and arrangements regarding venues, facilities, etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">2</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records relate to arrangement processes only. Retention supports the use of records for administrative purposes.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="3.3.0"><ID control="AR">416</ID><TermTitle>Grant assistance</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with receiving applications for and issuing grant funding to community groups, organisations or individuals.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Status><Submitted><Officer>Chris Eccles</Officer><Position>Director General</Position><Agency agencyno="10">Department of Premier and Cabinet</Agency><Date>2014-02-17</Date></Submitted><Approved>2014-04-10</Approved><Issued><Agency agencyno="10">Department of Premier and Cabinet</Agency><Date>2014-04-16</Date></Issued><Applying><Agency agencyno="10">Department of Premier and Cabinet</Agency><StartDate>2014-04-16</StartDate></Applying><Applying extent="part"><Agency agencyno="567">Department of Education and Communities</Agency><StartDate>2014-04-16</StartDate></Applying><Applying extent="part"><Agency agencyno="6441">Office of Communities</Agency><StartDate>2014-04-16</StartDate></Applying><Supersedes><IDRef control="FA">313</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>2011 version</AuthorityTitleRef><ItemNoRef>3.3.0</ItemNoRef><Date>2014-04-16</Date></Supersedes></Status><Class itemno="3.3.1" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records of:<List><Item>the deliberations and decisions of committees or panels responsible for the assessment of grant or funding applications</Item><Item>submissions to the Premier or responsible delegated officer concerning recommendations for grant or funding approvals</Item><Item>records documenting the Premier's or delegated officer's approval or variance of these recommendations</Item><Item>summary records or registers of grant applications (successful or unsuccessful) </Item><Item>final reports that detail the outcome of projects.</Item></List></Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 3. Records document the nature of people’s interaction with government and its influence on the administration of government.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2011 for committee records, submissions to Premier, and records documenting Premier’s approval.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark: Consistent with South Australia</Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2011</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records document the nature and impact of government interaction with the community.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In response to comments received from external consultation scope of class has been extended to encompass records of committees or panels involved in the assessment of grant or funding applications.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2014</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records document government decisions with respect to the disbursement of grants and funding to support community projects and initiatives. Consistent with current decisions applying under FA313, 3.3.1 (2011), extending scope of application to records documenting the Premier's or delegated officer's approval of any recommendations concerning the disbursement or allocation of funds. Ensures retention of summary grant application information where the information is not otherwise documented in records being retained as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2025</Emphasis> see AR573 - March 2025</Paragraph><Paragraph>Previously summary records of unsuccessful and successful grant applications were only required as State archives where the information or detail was not otherwise documented in the organisation’s annual report, committee or panel records or ministerial submissions.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This has been changed so that summary records of grants are required as State archives regardless of mentions in annual reports, committee records or panel reports. Details in annual reports can be minimal and access to information about grants will be facilitated by having the information in one place rather than in committee or panel records.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Final reports of the outcomes of projects have been added. These were not previously covered and identified as a gap.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 3.3.1 - Change to include all summary records of grant applications and to add final reports of the outcomes of projects</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.3.2" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Superseded see entry 3.3.3.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal/><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2011</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records document community interaction with government and decisions influencing the administration of government grants and funding.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2014</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Records document government support for community service delivery programs and initiatives of State or regional significance. Consistent with current decisions applying under FA313, 3.3.2 (20122) but clarifies, and removes Premier's approval as, criteria for types of funded projects or services warranting retention as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2025</Emphasis> see AR573 - March 2025</Paragraph><Paragraph>Previously this entry covered records of successful grant applications for projects or services of State or regional significance. This has been removed as application records tend to be operational. All grant applications are now covered in entry 3.3.3.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 3.3.2 - Superseded by FA313 3.3.3</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.3.3" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records of successful grants to support community projects or services within local communities. This includes records of the grant application and associated records relating to the administration and monitoring of the grant, including correspondence and consultation with and reports, papers or financial statements, etc., submitted by the grant recipient.</Paragraph><Paragraph>See <Source>Grants Administration Guide</Source> for requirements of administering NSW Government grants.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>all grant conditions are complete</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2011 for grants to support community projects.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark:<List><Item>Tasmania retains for 7 years after action completed.</Item><Item>South Australia retains for 5 years after action completed or grant acquitted</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2011</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period supports the accountability of the agency with respect to the administration of grants. Details of grant money or funds disbursed by the agency are recorded in the Department's annual reports. Where applications are assessed by a committee or panel the records and recommendations of the committee or panel are required as State archives under entry 3.3.1 above.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2014</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period supports accountability with respect to the administration of grants. Details of grants or funding disbursed by an agency are documented in their Annual report. Summary records, recommendations and approvals documenting the assessment of applications and allocation of funds are identified as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Consistent with current decisions applying under FA313, 3.3.3 (2011) but clarifies criteria with respect to records not required as State archives. These types of grant programs generally entail the contribution of financial support to projects undertaken or services delivered by councils or non-profit community groups and organisations. The grants programs will generally entail the distribution of small amounts of money to support a variety of community based projects, services or organisations. The NSW Government's contribution is usually only a proportion of the total cost of the community projects which they fund.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2025</Emphasis> see AR573 - March 2025</Paragraph><Paragraph>Previously successful grant applications for projects or services of State or regional significance were required as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This has been removed so that all grant applications are retained for 7 years after the project is finalised. Grant applications tend to be operational records and the records of successful grants being retained as State archives under entry 4 (deliberations and decisions of committees or panels, submissions to the Premier, Premier’s approval, summary records of grants, and reports of outcomes) meet State archives needs.</Paragraph><Paragraph>7 years complies with the NSW Government <Source>Grants Administration Guide</Source>.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 3.3.3 - Expanded to include all successful grant applications</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.3.4" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the assessment of grant applications that are unsuccessful.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>☐ Precedent:</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark:<List><Item>Tasmania retains for 3 years.</Item><Item>South Australia retains for 5 years after action completed.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2011</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention supports the accountability of the agency for following due process with respect to the assessment of grant applications. Summary details of unsuccessful applicants are required as State archives under entry 3.3.1 above. Where applications are assessed by a committee or panel the records and recommendations of the committee or panel are required as State archives under entry 3.3.1 above.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2014</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>This is a reduction of current retention requirements under FA313, 3.3.4 from a minimum of 7 years to 2 years. The amended retention period is sufficient to support the accountability of the agency with respect to assessment processes. Details of grants or funding disbursed by an agency are documented in their Annual report. Summary records documenting the receipt and assessment of applications and recommendations and approvals concerning the allocation of funds are identified as State archives. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Note: Retention period increased from 2 to 4 years for accountability and potential reference at request of State Records Board (April meeting 2014, see D14/7686)</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2025</Emphasis> see AR573 - March 2025</Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period increased from 4 to 7 years to meet audit requirements.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 3.3.4 - No change</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.3.5" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Superseded. See entry 3.3.1</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal/><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination:</Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: </Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2018</Emphasis></Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period supports accountability with respect to the administration of grants. Details of grants or funding disbursed by an agency are documented in their Annual report. Summary records, recommendations and approvals documenting the assessment of applications and allocation of funds are identified as State archives.</Paragraph><Paragraph><Emphasis>2025</Emphasis> see AR573 - March 2025</Paragraph><Paragraph>Previously this entry which covered summary records or registers of grant program applications with a minimum retention period of 7 years. Summary records are now covered by entry 3.3.1 and are required as State archives.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA313 3.3.5 - Superseded by FA331 3.3.1</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="3.4.0"><TermTitle>Policy</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with developing and establishing policy decisions relating to development and delivery of services and programs to the community.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY SUPPORT - COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the development of policies and guidelines for people to sit on boards and committees.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="3.4.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to development of whole of government or multiple agency policy concerning the provision of services and programs to the general community or to targeted community groups, where the agency takes a lead role in development and implementation of the policy. Records include guidelines setting the criteria for the involvement of the agency in service delivery projects or improvement activities, policy proposals, background research, records of consultations or meetings, draft versions of policies containing significant changes or alterations or formally circulated for comment, reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation with stakeholders etc. </Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the formulation or determination of policy across the whole of government and key decisions influencing the administration of government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="3.5.0"><TermTitle>Programs</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The process of managing a set of procedures, activities, resources, related projects and/or management strategies that are usually ongoing. </Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY SUPPORT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Service coordination</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to projects initiated to resolve local issues requiring interagency coordination</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PUBLIC SECTOR PERFORMANCE REVIEW</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Program performance improvement</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for state wide strategies to address structural issues in the performance and delivery of programs in the New South Wales public sector.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="3.5.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to programs or schemes developed to address issues affecting or to support the development and delivery of services to the general community or to targeted community groups e.g. programs to assist community groups with employment and settlement, support volunteering or crime prevention and community safety programs.  Includes records documenting programs of work, consultation and liaison with other organisations, agencies or community groups, guidelines and publications developed to support the programs. Also includes records documenting the evaluation, assessment or reporting on the outcomes of the programs.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the nature and impact of government activities on the community. </Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" update="2025-02-27" itemno="3.7.0"><TermTitle>Representations</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Representations to the Premier by members of the public, individual organisations, other agencies or Members of Parliament on behalf of a constituent seeking formal response.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advice</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to briefing notes prepared for other Ministers.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="3.7.1" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to responses to correspondence, petitions, campaigns or continuing issues received by the Premier where a submission has been prepared for the authorisation of a reply by a senior officer of the relevant Department or the Premier/Minister. Records include:<List><Item>copies of letters received</Item><Item>draft responses</Item><Item>minutes providing details</Item><Item>requests for changes</Item><Item>final responses.</Item></List></Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 1. Records document the nature and impact of government activities on the community.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark: Consistent with Queensland.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Previously these records were covered in FA254 and have been moved into FA313 to simplify disposal.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 2.2.1 - No change</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.7.2" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to responses to correspondence, petitions or campaigns received by the Premier where the response is a form letter/template noting the matters raised or that the matter has been referred to the relevant Minister. Records include:<List><Item>copies of letters received</Item><Item>draft responses</Item><Item>final responses.</Item></List></Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark: Tasmania retains for 2 years. The Office of the Governor of NSW retains similar records until administrative or reference use ceases. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Previously these records were covered in FA254 and have been moved into FA313 to simplify disposal. The Department receives between 60,000 to 100,000 of these representations every year.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 2.2.2 - No change</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="3.6.0"><TermTitle>Service coordination</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The processes involved in coordinating and facilitating the delivery of government services to communities in NSW. Includes regional forums and task forces convened to resolve particular issues of concern to local communities.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY SUPPORT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Programs</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for the development of programs</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to project committees or task forces coordinated by other government agencies</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="3.6.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to projects initiated to resolve issues associated with local service delivery or local problems requiring interagency coordination where the organisation is the lead agency, NSW representative or has secretariat responsibility. Includes records of meetings of groups, committees, etc established or convened to coordinate activities, including records of associated correspondence and business arising, records of forums and meetings held with other agencies and/or community representatives relating to the issue or project, agreements or memoranda of understanding with other organisations, agencies, community groups, etc concerning coordination or implementation of the project, project action plans, reports and issues papers relating to the project, its progress, outcomes etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the nature and impact of government activities on the community. </Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="3.6.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the provision of advice and reports to the Premier on interagency projects initiated to resolve issues associated with local service delivery or local problems where the organisation is not the lead or primary coordinating agency. </Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of key activities influencing the administration of government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class></Term></Term><Term type="function" itemno="4.0.0" update="2011-08-03"><TermTitle>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of preparing for and responding to natural disasters, security threats, terrorism and other emergencies within the State. This includes co-ordination and support of emergency services organisations as well as the analysis, co-ordination and development of policies, procedures and guidelines.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Term type="activity" itemno="4.1.0"><TermTitle>Advice</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with offering opinions by or to the organisation as to an action or judgment. Includes the process of advising.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Emergency and disaster response</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to post emergency event de-briefing and analysis</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Reviewing</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to advice associated with reviews of programs and operations</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to representation on interagency and national committees.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.1.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the formulation and provision of advice on security and emergency management issues. This may include advice provided to the Premier, Cabinet, heads of agencies, interagency and inter government committees, non-government organisations or the private sector. Records include:<List><Item>briefing notes</Item><Item>minutes</Item><Item>reports</Item><Item>correspondence, and </Item><Item>associated source data supporting the advice.</Item></List></Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the background to and basis for key decisions influencing the administration of government and governance of the people of NSW.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.2.0"><TermTitle>Community Liaison</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with maintaining regular general contact between the Government, community groups, the private sector etc. concerning security and emergency management.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.2.1" update="2011-07-22"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records of liaison and meetings with community leaders and representatives of community groups to discuss matters or issues relating to the management or minimisation of security risks.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the nature of government interaction with and the impact of government activities on the community and individuals within the community.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In response to comments received from external consultation disposal class description amended to distinguish between nature and types of community interaction covered by classes under this activity and to remove potential limitation to subjective assessment of 'high risk' over time.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="4.2.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to general liaison and information exchange with community groups concerning security or emergency management arrangements or initiatives.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports reference use of records for the maintenance of ongoing community interaction. Records relating to the formulation and provision of advice on security and emergency management issues to non-government organisations or the private sector are identified as State archives and to meetings with community leaders and representatives of community groups to discuss matters or issues relating to the management or minimisation of security risks as identified as State archives under 4.2.1 above.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.3.0"><TermTitle>Emergency and disaster response</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with the response to emergencies arising from acts of terrorism, natural disasters and other incidents.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.3.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the response to emergencies, natural disasters or incidents that have a significant impact on the State or a particular region or locality and its residents. This includes emergencies, natural disasters or incidents that are declared State emergencies or disasters, that result in major loss of life, injury or damage to property or that have a notable impact e.g. there is formal inquiry into the emergency either in relation to its causes or handling, the emergency results in substantial changes to legislation or government policy, the emergency was the result of a terrorist act or deliberate attempt or act of sabotage against the government. Records include activation and operation of the State crisis centre, liaison with police, emergency services and other State, local and Commonwealth Government and their agencies, de-briefing provided during and after the emergency, reviews of the response and recommendations for future action such as improvements in response times, coordination of services or intelligence gathering/information requirements etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records relate to events of significance to the broader community, State or nation and document the background to key decisions and activities influencing the handling of major emergencies or disasters.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 4</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="4.3.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the response to emergency incidents that have a limited impact on persons or property (i.e. do not involve significant loss of life or major injury or damage to property within the State or a particular region or locality or do not have major policy/legislative impact). Records include liaison with police, emergency services and other State, local and Commonwealth Government and their agencies, de-briefing provided during and after the emergency, reviews of the response and recommendations for future action.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">10</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention provides evidence of the agency's emergency response actions and also provides precedent for actions in similar future situations.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="4.3.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to pro-active incident, emergency or crisis response coordination and planning for major events (such as World Youth Day and Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC)), that are incident free or where incidents are minor. Includes debriefings, reviews and recommendations for the management of future events.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the implementation of government plans and strategies for the management and averting of crisis at major events. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Entry added in response to comments received from external consultation recommending retention of these records as State archives.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="4.3.4"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to routine correspondence, enquiries and information about emergency arrangements.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports potential ongoing use for operational reference. Records contain information of routine nature and are unlikely to be required for legal or accountability purposes with respect to the management or handling of an incident.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.4.0"><TermTitle>Exercises &amp; training</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with State and interjurisdictional exercises to test preparedness to respond to and recover from emergencies arising from act of terrorism, natural disasters and other incidents.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.4.1" update="2011-07-18"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the conduct of the exercises to test preparedness for emergencies or security incidents. Includes records relating to the establishment of exercises, invitations to participate in exercises, staffing arrangements, the use and supply of equipment, handbooks, training documentation, the umpiring of exercises in other jurisdictions.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports the reuse of records for subsequent exercises. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period increased from 5 to 7 years in response to comments received from external consultation recommending 7 would be preferable as exercises might take place less frequently than every 5 years.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.5.0"><TermTitle>Implementation</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with carrying out or putting into action, plans, policies, procedures or instructions.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.5.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the implementation of recommendations from formal Inquiries into an emergency incident e.g. in relation to its causes or handling.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of the deliberations, decisions and actions of State Government and public sector bodies relating to key functions and programs and significant issues faced in governing the State.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.6.0"><TermTitle>Media &amp; Public Information Campaigns</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Information campaigns designed to disseminate the Government's message in relation to national and State security.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.6.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to media and public information campaigns to promote counter-terrorism and security awareness among the general community. Includes campaigns planned as part of national information campaigns. Records include project briefs, project plans, approved drafts, proofs of posters, leaflets and web sites, campaign launches etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document conditions within the State at a particular point in time.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.7.0"><TermTitle>Planning</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The process of formulating ways in which objectives can be achieved. Includes determination of services, needs and solutions to those needs.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.7.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the formulation and development of plans and strategic initiatives for emergency, security or disaster preparedness and response within the State where the agency has a major input into planning processes. Records include planning or project proposals and approvals, background research, draft versions of plans containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, notes of meetings or reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation with stakeholders etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records demonstrate State Government efforts to ensure the security and safety of the people of NSW as well as providing evidence of the process of Government decision making on these issues at the highest level of government in the State.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="4.7.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the formulation and development of plans and strategic initiatives for emergency, security or disaster preparedness and response within the State where the agency has no or only minor input into planning processes. Records include draft versions of plans or reports received for comment or information purposes.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records retained for reference value and reuse in further planning exercises. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period increased from 5 to 7 years in response to comments received from external consultation recommending 7 would be preferable as planning exercises might take place less frequently than every 5 years.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Department is not the primary coordinating, planning or management agency with respect to the development of these types of plans or strategies and this entry covers records of circumstances where the agency has no or only minor input into planning processes. Records relating to the formulation of plans are identified as State archives in functional retention and disposal authorities for NSW Police (DA220, entries 6.6.2, 6.9.1 and 6.9.2) and NSW Health (DA25, entries 27.1.1 - 27.1.4), agencies with primary planning and coordination responsibilities and will be identified as State archives in functional retention and disposal authorities for the other emergency policy, planning and coordination agencies as these are developed.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="4.7.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to planning for the protection of current and former New South Wales office holders. Records include manuals, risk assessments of office holders, risk plans and risk escalation plans in the event of an incident.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the formulation of strategic management decisions across sectors.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.8.0"><TermTitle>Policy</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with developing and establishing decisions, directions and precedents which act as a reference for future decision making, as the basis from which the organisation's operating procedures are determined.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.8.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the policy coordination of the Government's response to terrorism events and threats. Records include policy proposals, background research, records of consultations, draft versions of policies containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation with stakeholders.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the formulation and determination of policy across the whole of government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.9.0"><TermTitle>Procedures</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Standard methods of operating laid down by an organisation according to formulated policies.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.9.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of procedures governing counter-terrorism response for NSW Government agencies. Includes input into national procedures, manuals or handbook (such as the national Counter-terrorism handbook). Records include background research, draft versions of procedures containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation with stakeholders.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document key activities relating to or influencing the handling of emergencies or security issues faced by the State.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="4.9.2" update="2011-07-18"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of counter-terrorism training manuals and instructional material for use in the NSW Government.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records retained for reference and reuse of material. Records relating to the development of Procedures, including input into national handbooks and manuals are retained as State archives (see entry above). Circulars and memos documenting advice issued to agencies concerning procedures, protocols, etc. are also retained as State archives (see under STRATEGIC POLICY AND ADVICE - Policy)</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.10.0"><TermTitle>Programs</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The process of managing a set of procedures, activities, resources, related projects and/or management strategies that are usually ongoing.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Reviewing</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to reviews of programs</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.10.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to development of programs for supporting or coordinating emergency, security or disaster preparedness and response within the State where the agency has a major input into or responsibility for the program. Includes training programs developed for NSW Government agencies. Records include background research, draft versions of reports containing substantial changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, final, approved versions of proposals concerning changes, the outcomes of meetings with program stakeholders etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of the deliberations, decisions and actions of State Government and public sector bodies relating to key programs concerned with counter-terrorism, State security and disaster preparedness.  </Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="4.10.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to development of programs for supporting or coordinating emergency, security or disaster preparedness and response within the State where the agency plays a non-significant role or they are Commonwealth run programs. Records include background research, draft versions of programs containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, notes of meetings or reports analysing issues and the outcomes of stakeholders including Commonwealth and other State parties.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records retained for reference.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="4.11.0"><TermTitle>Reviewing</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities involved in re-evaluating or re-examining products, processes, procedures, standards and systems. Includes recommendations and advice resulting from these activities.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GDA">12</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Personnel records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>PERSONNEL</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Security</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to security clearances</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="4.11.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to reviews of government programs and operations for managing and responding to natural disasters, security threats, terrorism and other emergencies within the State. Records include - documents establishing the review, background research, draft versions of review reports containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, final and approved versions of reports, project or action plans.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of the deliberations, decisions and actions of State Government and public sector bodies relating to key issues of security and counter-terrorism that substantially impact upon the security of the State and the community of NSW.  They therefore warrant retention as State archives.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term></Term><Term type="function" itemno="5.0.0"><TermTitle>MINISTERIAL AND PARLIAMENTARY SERVICES</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of supporting elected officials in the execution of their duties. Includes Ministers' offices support, including the Premier as well as Executive support and support for the Leader of the Opposition and former Office Holders.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC POLICY AND ADVICE</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Policy</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for ministerial memoranda issued by the Premier</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Term type="activity" itemno="5.1.0"><TermTitle>Audit</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with officially checking quality assurance and operational records, systems or processes to confirm legislation, directions and regulations have been adhered to or that operations are carried out efficiently, economically and in compliance with requirements. Includes audits of Ministers' offices administrative processes and office expenditure.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Audit</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to formal audits of accounts or the management of financial resources.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Audit</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to organisation-wide audits across functions</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="5.1.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the conduct of audits of Ministers' offices administrative processes and expenditure which identify major irregularities and lead to findings of misuse or inappropriate practices. Records include records of audit planning, liaison with auditing bodies, minutes or notes of meetings, notes taken at interviews, correspondence, draft versions of audit reports containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, final, approved versions of audit reports, records of any remedial action taken.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Information in these records may document events that are controversial in the administration of the State and demonstrate efforts by Government to improve the probity of government administration. Some may become part of broader and sometimes controversial inquiries into the administration of Ministers' offices.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="5.1.2" update="2011-07-15"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the conduct of audits of Ministers' offices administrative processes and expenditure which are routine. Records include records of audit planning, liaison with auditing bodies, minutes or notes of meetings, notes taken at interviews, correspondence, draft versions of audit reports containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, final, approved versions of audit reports, records of any remedial action taken.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports the accountability of the audit activity and also the requirements of the agency to refer to past audit exercises to ensure consistency and efficiency in the audit process.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term itemno="5.2.0"><TermTitle>Leave</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The administration of applications for leave.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="5.2.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to notices and approvals of Ministerial absences by the Premier.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>These relate to routine notifications to the Premier of Ministerial absences and associated approvals. The Constitution Act (ss36 and 37) makes provision for the continuation of administration when a Minister is absent from the State or unable, through illness or for other reasons, to act in their Portfolio. The Governor may authorise a Minister to act for or on behalf of another Minister during their absence. Records of the Executive Council would document any acting arrangements approved by the Governor.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="5.3.0"><TermTitle>Policy</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with developing and establishing decisions, directions and precedents which act as a reference for future decision making, as the basis from which the organisation's operating procedures are determined.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Policy</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to advice or notifications regarding policies that apply to the whole-of-government, e.g. Premier's Memoranda and Circulars, Treasurer's Directions.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Submissions</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to submissions by the organisation on the development or review of government-wide policies developed by central coordinating agencies.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Policy</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the organisation's policies on cross-functional or organisation-wide matters.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>implementation</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the implementation of government-wide policies by the organisation.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="5.3.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development and review of policies and codes of conduct for Ministers and ministerial staff. Records include policy proposals, background research, records of consultations, draft versions of policies containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation with stakeholders and final versions of policies and codes of conduct. This includes the Ministerial handbook and associated guidelines and correspondence regarding the application of policies and responsibilities for their implementation.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the implementation of policy applying to ministers of Government with respect to their responsibilities and the conduct of their office.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="5.4.0"><TermTitle>Security (includes Ministerial protection)</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities involved in providing security protection to current and former New South Wales office holders.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Planning</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to risk assessments and the development of plans for the protection of current and former office holders.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Security</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the protection of current and former office holder's residential and business premises.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="5.4.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to major security occurrences, such as terrorist attacks, assassination attempts, break-ins, involving current and former office holders or their families. Includes records of liaison and reports relating to the incident and its handling.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the nature of people’s interaction with government and key activities influencing the governance of NSW.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="5.4.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to liaison activities and reports concerning security and protection for current and former office holders or their families where there was no security occurrence or the security occurrence was of a non threatening nature (e.g. a false alarm).</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period is consistent with periods applying to records relating to minor security breaches or incidents in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records</Source> (GA28, 16.24.3). </Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period increased from 3 to 7 years in response to comments received from external consultation noting that matters of an initially minor nature may over the course of time become major. </Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="5.4.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to arrangements for the personal security of current and former office holders.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">3</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for administrative and reference purposes.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term></Term><Term type="function" itemno="6.0.0"><TermTitle>PROTOCOL AND EVENTS</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of delivering or coordinating government support for special events and providing ceremonial, protocol or hospitality services to visiting guests of the government. Includes the management of State aspects of the Australian Honours system and supporting the Governor of NSW in their ceremonial and community roles.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY SUPPORT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Grant assistance</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the funding or sponsorship of community events</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Term type="activity" itemno="6.1.0"><TermTitle>Awards and honours</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Titles, certificates or decorations conferred on persons as a token of respect or in recognition of service, distinction or achievement.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PUBLIC SECTOR EMPLOYMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Awards and honours</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the award of the Public Service Medals</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Celebrations, ceremonies, functions</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to administrative arrangements for functions to present awards</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Celebrations, ceremonies, functions</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the receipt of awards by the agency</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="6.1.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the administration of awards schemes, for example the Premiers and Australia Day Awards, by the agency. Records include nominations for awards, decisions on granting award and details of award recipients.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of the activities and recognition of individuals or organisations that have significantly contributed to society.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 4</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="6.2.0"><TermTitle>Celebrations, ceremonies and functions</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with arranging and managing festivities or celebrations to honour a particular event or occasion.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PROTOCOL AND EVENTS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Committees</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records of committees established to plan and coordinate particular events</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PROTOCOL AND EVENTS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Community events and programs</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to sponsorship programs</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PROTOCOL AND EVENTS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Official visits</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to hospitality functions associated with official visits</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="FA">254</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Cabinet Secretariat, policy advice and support services to the Government</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>CO-ORDINATION OF GOVERNMENT, MAJOR PROJECTS AND LEGAL SERVICES</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Visits</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to overseas visits made or proposed to be made by Ministers</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the management of issues associated with intellectual property, use of logos etc</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Celebrations, ceremonies, functions</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to catering, transport and venue bookings for events.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="6.2.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Key records relating to government ceremonies, festivities or celebrations, this includes annual events (e.g. ANZAC Day and Australia Day) and one-off public events or ceremonies to mark a specific event or occasion (e.g. Welcome home parades, Opening of Parliament, State Funerals, memorial services). Records include development and approval of events, funding details, merchandising, badgeing, programs, guest lists, selected official photos, including funding details, official patrons and reports relating to the occasion or event or programs associated with the event.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records relate to events or persons of significance to the broader community or State of NSW Records and document the staging of significant cultural events or celebrations.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 4</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="6.2.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the coordination of arrangements for ceremonies, festivities, celebrations or events. Records include event planning, marketing and media relations, liaison and consultation with other government agencies or levels of government or the community sector.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for ongoing administrative or reference purposes.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="6.2.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to arrangements for Government exhibitions or displays at community events such as agricultural shows, trade shows, sporting events or exhibitions. Includes records relating to administrative arrangements for the mounting of displays such as transport, equipment, facilities.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period consistent with that identified for records relating to the mounting of exhibitions and displays in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records</Source> (GA28, 2.10.1).</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="6.3.0"><TermTitle>Committees</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with the management of committees and task forces (internal and external, private, local, state, Commonwealth etc.).</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the establishment and meetings of Boards and advisory committees, councils etc and administrative arrangements for meetings</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="6.3.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the establishment and meetings of committees, councils, etc. established for the purposes of coordinating or delivering particular special events, e.g. the Australia Day Council, the Committee for the Sesquicentenary of Responsible Government in NSW. Includes records relating to the committee's establishment, terms of reference, appointment of members, resignations and declarations of pecuniary interests, proceedings, minutes, reports, agendas etc. </Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the planning, management, staging of significant cultural events and celebrations.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 4</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="6.4.0"><TermTitle>Emblem administration</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with managing State emblems including the Coat of Arms, Floral Emblem, and the State flag. Includes the protection of emblems, the processing of requests for usage and reproduction and the provision of flags to community groups and organisations.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="6.4.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the management of New South Wales Emblems, State flag and the New South Wales Coat of Arms. Records include memoranda and circulars issued by the agency stipulating the how State symbols may be used, the conditions under which applications may be made and approvals for use where the permission given is of a permanent nature.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>As these are the key symbolic emblems of the State, policy records relating to their use indicate the development of official attitudes to the use of state emblems over time.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="6.4.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the provision of advice to both government and the public on the use of State symbols. Includes records relating to the provision of access to image libraries and approvals of artwork.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention consistent with Statute of Limitations for negligent misstatement.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="6.4.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to requests by organisations and individuals to use State symbols on a one off or temporary basis. Records includes requests and responses giving or denying permission.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>permission expires or is superseded</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention enables tracking of permitted use of symbols.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="6.5.0"><TermTitle>Official visits</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities involved in coordinating visits to Australia by guests of the New South Wales Government. Includes visits by the Royal Family, foreign heads of government and representatives of foreign governments.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PROTOCOL AND EVENTS - PROTOCOL &amp; PROCEDURES</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to policy governing the correct protocol and precedence to follow during official visits.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="FA">254</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Cabinet Secretariat, policy advice and support services to the Government</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>CO-ORDINATION OF GOVERNMENT, MAJOR PROJECTS AND LEGAL SERVICES</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Visits</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to overseas visits made or proposed to be made by Ministers</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Corruption</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the management of official gifts</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="6.5.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to visits by the Royal Family, foreign Heads of State, Heads of Government and other leading dignitaries, including the Secretary-General of the United Nations. Includes records of organising and managing official or formal social occasions, liaison and coordination with Commonwealth authorities, programs and guest lists for hosted functions, selected official photos, reports, etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records relate to visits by persons of significance to the State.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 4</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="6.5.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to private/transit visits or cancelled official guest of government visits.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">10</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports potential reference use of the records.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="6.5.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to visits to New South Wales by other guests of the government, including Ministers of foreign governments. Includes records of organising and managing official or formal social occasions, liaison and coordination with Commonwealth authorities etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">10</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports the administrative use of records for reference and for subsequent planning of similar visits.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="6.6.0"><TermTitle>Protocol &amp; Procedures</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Policy and procedures governing the management of protocol and conduct or staging of events.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PROTOCOL AND EVENTS - EMBLEM ADMINISTRATION</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to management and use of the State symbols, flags and emblems</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="6.6.1" update="2011-07-18"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to development of protocols for State or government ceremonies, forms of address, and tables of precedence and flag procedures. Includes Aboriginal Cultural Protocols and Practices Policy established by the office.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the formulation of high level policy within the organisation.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="6.6.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of policies or policy advice to government concerning the management or staging of events e.g. user pays policy for private sector events </Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the nature of private sector interaction with government in staging of major cultural events. </Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="6.6.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of procedures for the management or holding of events.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">10</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for administrative and reference purposes and for accountability purposes should issues arise in relation to the management of an event.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term></Term><Term type="function" itemno="7.0.0" update="2025-02-27"><TermTitle>PUBLIC SECTOR EMPLOYMENT</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of managing employment and remuneration practices for people working in the State Public Service including State/sector wide policy, procedures and guidelines. Includes the negotiation of industrial awards and agreements, the provision of assistance to agencies to resolve industrial relations and employment matters, workforce planning and management with respect to data collection, superannuation, capability development, executive services, recruitment, ethics, occupational health and safety, redeployment and relocation, and equity and diversity.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="FA">329</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Public Service Commission</AuthorityTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to public sector workforce planning and management</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Status><Applying extent="part"><Agency agencyno="6315">Department of Finance and Services</Agency><StartDate>2013-08-09</StartDate></Applying></Status><Term type="activity" itemno="7.1.0" update="2024-10-29"><TermTitle>Advice</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Entries superseded by FA329, <Source>Public sector workforce planning and management.</Source></Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="FA">239</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Public Sector workforce planning and management.</AuthorityTitleRef></SeeReference></TermDescription></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="7.2.0" update="2024-10-29"><TermTitle>Advocacy</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Entries superseded by FA329, <Source>Public sector workforce planning and management.</Source></Paragraph></TermDescription></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="7.3.0" update="2024-10-29"><TermTitle>Awards and honours</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Entries superseded by FA329, <Source>Public sector workforce planning and management.</Source></Paragraph></TermDescription></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="7.4.0"><TermTitle>Industrial awards and agreements</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities relating to negotiations and consultation with representative organisations on industrial matters affecting the public sector workforce.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PUBLIC SECTOR EMPLOYMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advice</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the provision of advice to agencies undertaking negotiations with unions</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PUBLIC SECTOR EMPLOYMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advocacy</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for submissions or representations to courts or tribunals on industrial relations matters</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PUBLIC SECTOR EMPLOYMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Reviewing</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to reviews of agency bargaining claims against service wide guidelines</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Agreements</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to workplace or other agreements that the agency negotiates with its own employees.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="7.4.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the negotiation of awards and agreements governing public sector employment conditions. Records include final versions of industrial awards and agreements and any variations, minutes of meetings or consultation processes, correspondence relating to the negotiation  of terms and conditions etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of key activities influencing the administration of government and terms and conditions of public sector employees.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 5</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="7.5.0" update="2024-10-29"><TermTitle>Learning And Development (Training)</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Entries superseded by FA329, <Source>Public sector workforce planning and management.</Source></Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Joint ventures</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the development of programs and agreements with other State and federal government agencies or with service providers.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Planning</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records of operational plans for delivering programs</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>TENDERING or CONTRACTING OUT</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the issue and assessment of tenders for the provision of courses or training services or the evaluation of contracted service providers</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="7.6.0" update="2024-10-29"><TermTitle>Policy</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Entries superseded by FA329, <Source>Public sector workforce planning and management.</Source></Paragraph></TermDescription></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="7.7.0" update="2024-10-29"><TermTitle>Workforce planning &amp; management</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Entries 7.7.1 to 7.7.7 superseded by FA329, <Source>Public sector workforce planning and management.</Source></Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="7.7.8"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Record relating to applications for exemptions to advertise Senior Executive Service (SES) positions. Records include requests received and decisions on the applications.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence that proper processes were implemented in accordance with relevant legislation to seek the exemption.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term></Term><Term type="function" itemno="8.0.0"><TermTitle>PUBLIC SECTOR PERFORMANCE REVIEW</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of reviewing regulatory regimes and public sector structures, performance and accountability and developing sector-wide, service or agency specific strategies for improvement. </Paragraph></TermDescription><Status><Applying extent="part"><Agency agencyno="6315">Department of Finance and Services</Agency><StartDate>2013-08-09</StartDate></Applying></Status><Term type="activity" itemno="8.1.0"><TermTitle>Program or agency performance review and improvement</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities involved in evaluating or examining the performance of government programs or agencies and the monitoring of initiatives or management of projects to achieve improved program outcomes or address issues affecting agency performance. Reviews may include agency and/or program reviews, major structural reviews involving multiple agencies, targeted agency or functional area reviews as requested by Cabinet.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY SUPPORT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Service coordination</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to coordination of services in regional areas to address local conditions or issues and reporting through regional coordination groups.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>CONTRACTING-OUT</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to contracting out of projects.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="8.1.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to projects initiated for the purpose of assisting Government agencies to achieve better service outcomes and address impediments to effective performance. Includes Premier's priority projects. Records include project plans, project briefs, liaison and meetings with agencies, action plans, final reports.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the background to and outcomes of key activities influencing the administration of government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="8.1.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to reviews of government agencies, programs and functions for the purpose of providing recommendations to government on improvements to the cost and quality of service delivery. Includes reports to the Council on the Cost and Quality of Government.  Records include project plans, advice to the Premier, establishment and operation of the project steering committee, correspondence with the agency, review working papers including drafts that have been approved or have been circulated for comment, research (including both documentary and survey data), discussion papers, reports to the project steering committee, review chronology, final reports or submissions relating to the findings and recommendations of the review, agency response to the review, implementation plans, monitoring schedule and correspondence of implementation.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of key decisions and activities influencing the administration of government.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="8.1.3" update="2011-07-15"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Reference documentation compiled in relation to agencies under review. Includes copies of documents received from agencies under review such as agency guidelines and policies, background information on the agency or services, agency publications, excerpts from legislation and regulations.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports use of records for reference and project review.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="8.2.0"><TermTitle>Regulation review and reform</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The processes involved in reviewing agency regulatory proposals, specific regulatory frameworks or areas and monitoring the implementation of regulatory reform processes. Includes development of guidelines and standards to assist Government agencies with development and review of legislation, regulations and other Statutory instruments.</Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>PUBLIC SECTOR PERFORMANCE REVIEW</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Reviewing</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to reviews of specific regulatory frameworks or areas</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="8.2.1" update="2011-08-03"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the assessment of regulatory proposals issued by Government agencies. Includes proposals that are not approved or proceeded with. Records include regulation statements submitted by agencies, assessments of regulatory proposals, consultations with agencies including meetings, amendments to proposals, advice to the Premier concerning a proposal, certificates of approval issued by the Premier or relevant Minister.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the development, implementation and review of legislation.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="8.2.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of policies, standards and guidelines for the making and review of legislation, regulations and other Statutory instruments. Records include background research, draft versions of procedures containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment, reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation stakeholders etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document key decisions and activities influencing the development of legislation and governance of the people of NSW.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="8.2.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to projects for improving regulation involving working with national or international organisations. Includes projects with the Council of Australian Governments and the Organisation of Economic Cooperation and Development. Records include project plans, meetings with project partners, project reports.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document key decisions and activities influencing the development, implementation and review of legislation.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="8.2.4"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to reporting on recommendations for regulatory review or reform and monitoring and reporting on progress in implementing regulatory reform. Includes responding to recommendations arising from reviews carried out by organisations such as the Independent Pricing and Regulatory Tribunal.  Records include monitoring, research, consultation with agencies etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the implementation of regulatory reform.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="8.2.5" update="2011-08-03"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the provision of general advice to Government agencies concerning regulatory proposal development processes, such as advice concerning the application, requirements or interpretation of standards or guidelines. </Paragraph><Paragraph>(For advice provided in relation the actual assessment of a submitted proposal use the disposal class relating to assessments of regulatory proposals.)</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">20</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for ongoing accountability regarding advice provided in relation to processes and procedures and potential reference purposes. This is advice relating to processes and procedures for developing and submitting proposals. Advice concerning the assessment of a specific regulatory proposal is required as State archives under entry 8.2.1 and policies, standards and guidelines for the making and review of legislation, regulations and other Statutory instruments are required as State archives under entry 8.2.2.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="8.2.6"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the advocacy within Government of improved regulatory performance. Records include submissions made to inquiries, advice made to the Premier, Cabinet and the Minister responsible for improving regulation.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of key decisions influencing the administration of government and governance of the people of NSW.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="8.2.7"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records of statistics, surveys and other raw data collected or collated for the purposes of regulatory review or reform projects.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the development, implementation and review of legislation.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In response to comments received from external consultation scope of class has been amended to identify records of statistics, surveys and other raw data collated or complied for the purposes of regulatory review or reform projects as State archives.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="8.2.8"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to projects for the review of regulatory regimes in NSW. Records include issues papers, briefs to Cabinet, Cabinet endorsement of the project scope, project plans, liaison and meetings with other agencies, consultation and meetings with industry stakeholders, legal research, interim recommendations in made in consultation with the responsible agencies, final reports with recommendations made to Cabinet, draft legislation.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the development, implementation and review of legislation.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="8.2.9"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Reference documentation compiled in relation to regulation review projects. Includes copies of documents collected or received from agencies in relation to the review such as guidelines and policies, agency publications, excerpts from legislation and regulations, literature reviews.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports use of records for reference and project review</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term></Term><Term type="function" itemno="9.0.0"><ID control="AR">490</ID><TermTitle>STATE INFRASTRUCTURE PROJECTS</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of facilitating the planning and development of State infrastructure.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="FA">439</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Infrastructure</AuthorityTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to infrastructure assurance and delivery of infrastructure projects.</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to submissions made to the Commonwealth concerning proposed infrastructure projects</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Policy &amp; Procedures</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to policy, procedures and guidelines for infrastructure projects.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Status><Applying><Agency agencyno="6990">Infrastructure NSW</Agency><StartDate>2018-08-23</StartDate></Applying></Status></Term><Term type="function" itemno="10.0.0"><ID control="AR">490</ID><TermTitle>STRATEGIC POLICY AND ADVICE</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The function of providing policy advice to the Premier, Cabinet, Executive, Governing bodies, etc.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to the establishment of and participation in intergovernmental and interagency committees</SeeText></SeeReference><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Agreements</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to intergovernmental agreements between NSW and the Commonwealth or other States.</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Status><Applying><Agency agencyno="6990">Infrastructure NSW</Agency><StartDate>2018-08-23</StartDate></Applying></Status><Term type="activity" itemno="10.1.0"><TermTitle>Legal Policy</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities involved in providing legal advice to the Premier and Cabinet on issues of public policy governing the whole of the State, intergovernment relations and State and federal constitutional matters.</Paragraph><SeeReference><IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef><AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef><TermTitleRef>LEGAL SERVICES</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advice</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to legal advice provided to Premier &amp; Cabinet</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="10.1.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to election writs for NSW State elections and by-elections.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of the source of authority and machinery of the State Government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 1</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.1.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the provision of advice to the Premier concerning the administration of casual vacancies within the Parliament.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document advice concerning the administration of Parliament. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Entry added in response to comments received from external consultation recommending retention of these records as State archives.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="10.1.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the receipt of advice from the Legislative Assembly on election timetables and the return of writs for the administration of casual vacancies in the NSW legislative assembly.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for administrative and reference purposes. Legislative Assembly vacancies are filled though by-elections which are administered/arranged through the Legislative Assembly. The DPC does not usually prepare any documents in relation to this process but receives advice from the Legislative Assembly of the proposed election timetable and return of the writs. Records relating to the issue of election writs and of advice originating within the Department relating to the administration of Parliamentary vacancies are identified as State archives under entries 10.1.1 and 10.1.2 above.</Paragraph></Justification></Class><Class itemno="10.1.4"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the registration of lobbyists. Includes the register, application forms, advice and decisions on applications, notification of applicants.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records establish the rights of individuals or groups to participate in the affairs of the State.</Paragraph></Justification><Status><Applying extent="part"><Agency agencyno="1157">New South Wales Electoral Commission</Agency></Applying></Status><Comment author="SRNSW"><Paragraph>As of 1/12/2014 responsibility for maintaining the Register of Third-Party Lobbyists and the prosecution of electoral offences was transferred from Department of Premier and Cabinet to the NSW Electoral Commission. </Paragraph></Comment></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="10.2.0"><TermTitle>Legislation</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The process of making laws. </Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC POLICY AND ADVICE</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>Advice</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records relating to advice provided to the Premier on the legislative proposals of other agencies</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="10.2.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the provision of advice and support to agencies on the development of legislation where the portfolio agency has primary carriage of the development of the legislation. Records include briefing notes and minutes providing advice to the Minister, comments on Cabinet submissions and proposals, correspondence, copies of drafting material including regulation impact statements, Explanatory Memoranda, reading speeches prepared for the portfolio Minister etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the development of legislation.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.2.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of legislation for whole of government purposes where the agency has primary carriage of the development process. Records include consultations with relevant agencies, organisations and stakeholders, advice to the Premier and other agencies, legislative drafting material including regulatory impact statements, second and subsequent reading speeches and preparation of Explanatory Memoranda.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the development of legislation.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="10.3.0"><TermTitle>Liaison</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with maintaining regular general contact between the organisation and other government agencies.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="10.3.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to routine liaison activities and information exchange undertaken with Commonwealth, State and/or local government organisations in order to assist in the coordination of government administration or projects. </Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for reference purposes.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="10.4.0" update="2025-02-27"><TermTitle>Policy</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The activities associated with developing and establishing decisions, directions and precedents which act as a reference for future decision making, as the basis from which the organisation’s operating procedures are determined. Include policy responses to the findings of royal commissions and commissions of inquiry.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="10.4.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Master set of circulars or memoranda issued by the Premier/Department.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the implementation of policy across the whole of government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.4.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development and establishment of government policies that impact on whole-of-government or cross portfolio administration and/or have far reaching social or economic impact. Records include: policy proposals; research papers; results of  consultations; supporting reports; major drafts; final policy documents; national policy statements; working papers; comments made on such policies.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the formulation and determination of policy across the whole of government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.4.3" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Master set of advice or briefing notes on policy issues prepared for use by the Premier or other Ministers relating to anticipated questions that may be raised in Parliament.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 1. Provides evidence of advice influencing the decisions of the NSW Government.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark: Consistent with Queensland, Victoria, South Australia and Tasmania.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Previously these records were covered in FA254 and have been moved into FA313 to simplify disposal.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 1.1.1 - No change</LinkedTo></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="10.5.0"><TermTitle>Reporting</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>The processes involved in receiving reports from other organisations regarding their activities, including unsolicited reports received from not for profit organisations advertising their programs to the Premier's office. </Paragraph><SeeReference><TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC POLICY AND ADVICE</TermTitleRef><TermTitleRef>State plan development and reporting</TermTitleRef><SeeText>for records of reports received against State Plan targets, See State Planning</SeeText></SeeReference></TermDescription><Class itemno="10.5.1" update="2011-08-04"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to reports received from agencies of government and non-Government organisations for the purpose of keeping the Premier's office informed of their activities where issues dealt with in the reports are the subject of public interest or controversy or require further action by the office or Department. Records include copies of reports, covering letters, responses, etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of key activities influencing the administration of government or governance of the people of NSW.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.5.2"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to reports received from agencies of government and non-Government organisations for the purpose of keeping the organisation informed of their activities where issues dealt with in the reports require no further action from the organisation. Records include copies of reports, covering letters, etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for reference purposes.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Retention period increased from 2 to 5 years in response to comments received from external consultation recommending retention for a slightly longer period in case a matter that initially appeared straightforward may require further action or attention. </Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" itemno="10.6.0"><TermTitle>State plan development and reporting</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Activities associated with the development and implementation of key planning documents establishing objectives and priorities to guide the conduct and coordination of activities across government.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="10.6.1"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of planning documents establishing government priorities and objectives for action e.g. the State Plan, State Infrastructure Strategy Statements and associated plans to support the delivery of targets and actions e.g. priority delivery plans negotiated with key agencies, plans identifying priority infrastructure projects. Includes records of background research, submissions or advice from government agencies, notes of meetings or reports analysing issues and the outcomes of consultation with stakeholders and the community, final versions and draft versions containing significant changes/alterations or formally circulated for comment.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records provide evidence of key decisions influencing the administration of government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.6.2" update="2011-08-05"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to reporting by agencies against State plan or strategy targets. Includes reports by other areas of the organisation monitoring NSW Government agencies and programs performance against State plan or strategy targets, reports submitted by agencies concerning progress in meeting targets or outcomes and records of meetings with agencies to discuss reporting outcomes and progress towards them, such as agenda and minutes of meetings, advice, actions arising and follow up correspondence arising from business discussed.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Records document the implementation of high level policy and strategic management decisions across government.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Appraisal objective 2</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.6.3"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to the development of systems to manage performance reporting and monitoring of outcomes against planning initiatives. Records include background research, proposals and records relating to the implementation of systems e.g. notes of meetings, correspondence or reports relating to implementation issues and feedback or consultation with system users etc.</Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">2</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>system superseded</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Retention supports potential reference use for the development of further systems.</Paragraph></Justification></Class></Term><Term type="activity" update="2019-08-06" itemno="10.7.0"><TermTitle>Submissions</TermTitle><TermDescription><Paragraph>Submissions by members of the department, other agencies or Members of Parliament to the Premier and/or other Ministers for consideration.</Paragraph></TermDescription><Class itemno="10.7.1" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to submissions made to the Premier and/or senior departmental staff regarding legislative and major policy matters. Records include:<List><Item>reports</Item><Item>background research and briefing papers</Item><Item>Ministerial advice memoranda.</Item></List></Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 1. Provides evidence of advice influencing the decisions of the NSW Government.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008. </Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark:<List><Item>Consistent with Tasmania for submissions of significant or controversial issues.</Item><Item>Consistent with Victoria.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Previously these records were covered in FA254 and have been moved into FA313 to simplify disposal.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 2.3.1 - No change</LinkedTo></Class><Class itemno="10.7.2" update="2025-02-27"><ClassDescription><Paragraph>Records relating to submissions made to the Premier and/or senior department staff regarding non-legislative or routine matters.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Examples of these are: daily analyses of the press to identify matters that may be of interest to the Premier; collation of information about individuals or organisations that the Premier is meeting, or conferences that the Premier is attending. Records include:<List><Item>reports</Item><Item>background research and briefing papers</Item><Item>Ministerial advice memoranda.</Item></List></Paragraph></ClassDescription><Disposal><RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod><DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger><DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction></Disposal><Justification><Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph><Paragraph>☒ Benchmark:<List><Item>Consistent with Tasmania for submissions not of significant or controversial issues.</Item><Item>Consistent with Victoria for minor submissions and responses from public or stakeholders that are pro forma in nature.</Item></List></Paragraph><Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Previously these records were covered in FA254 and have been moved into FA313 to simplify disposal.</Paragraph></Justification><LinkedTo type="linking table">FA254 2.3.2 - No change</LinkedTo></Class></Term></Term></Authority>
