<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Authority xmlns="http://www.records.nsw.gov.au/schemas/RDA">
  <ID control="SRFileNo">18/0231</ID>
  <ID control="AR">488</ID>
  <ID control="FA">399</ID>
  <Scope>provision of programs and advisory services to farmers and landholders</Scope>
  <Status>
    <Submitted>
      <Officer>David Witherdin</Officer>
      <Position>Chief Executive Officer</Position>
      <Agency agencyno="6971">Local Land Services</Agency>
      <Date>2018-06-06</Date>
    </Submitted>
    <Approved>2018-06-21</Approved>
    <Issued>
      <Agency agencyno="6971">Local Land Services</Agency>
      <Date>2018-06-29</Date>
    </Issued>
    <Applying extent="whole">
      <Agency agencyno="6971">Local Land Services</Agency>
      <StartDate>2018-06-29</StartDate>
    </Applying>
    <Supersedes>
      <IDRef control="GA">29</IDRef>
      <AuthorityTitleRef>General retention and disposal authority: catchment management</AuthorityTitleRef>
      <Date>2018-06-29</Date>
    </Supersedes>
    <Supersedes>
      <IDRef control="GDA">20</IDRef>
      <AuthorityTitleRef>General retention and disposal authority: rural lands protection</AuthorityTitleRef>
      <Date>2018-06-29</Date>
    </Supersedes>
  </Status>
  <LinkedTo type="SRNSW function">Land and Resource Management</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="SRNSW function">Primary Industries</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">Agricultural education and training</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">Agricultural pest management</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">Agricultural research</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">Animal industry regulation</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="SRNSW activity">Plant industry regulation</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="mandate">Local Land Services Act 2013</LinkedTo>
  <Context type="appraisal report">
    <ContextTitle>Background</ContextTitle>
    <ContextContent>
      <Paragraph>Local Land Services (LLS) provide biosecurity, natural resource management, agricultural production and emergency management programs and advisory services to farmers and landholders. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>LLS functional records are currently covered by authorities for <Source>Rural lands protection </Source>(GDA20, approved 2005), C<Source>atchment management </Source>(GA29, approved 2007) and <Source>Primary industries assistance, regulation and development</Source> (FA258, approved 2008).</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>LLS recently initiated a review of the retention and disposal coverage provided by these authorities.</Paragraph>
    </ContextContent>
  </Context>
  <Context type="appraisal report">
    <ContextTitle>Issue</ContextTitle>
    <ContextContent>
      <Paragraph>A retention and disposal authority to supersede GDA20 and GA29 has been developed for approval. For the most part the disposal decisions in GDA20 and GA29 have been retained. Minimum retention periods for some records have been increased to ensure consistent periods apply to records supporting similar processes. Changes to retention and disposal practices include:<List><Item><Emphasis>reduction of the minimum retention periods </Emphasis>for veterinary and advisory services field staff diaries and for records relating to the planning, funding and establishment of natural resource management programs and projects in catchment areas from 10 to 7 years after action completed (entries 1.1.1, 1.6.1, 1.9.2, 1.16.2 and 1.17.2)</Item><Item><Emphasis>reduction of the minimum retention period</Emphasis> for records relating to the conduct of elections for local land board members to permit destruction of records in accordance with regulatory requirements (entry 1.4.1)</Item><Item><Emphasis>change to retention period</Emphasis> for records relating to the management and administration of schemes for the identification of stock from retain until identification system ceases being used to retain minimum of 7 years after action completed (entry 1.15.2). Registers of stock identification codes, brands or marks will continue to be required as State archives (entry 1.15.1 above).</Item><Item><Emphasis>changes to retention periods and disposal actions</Emphasis> for natural resource monitoring, evaluation and research data to identify unique data sets as State archives and permit disposal of other data when no longer required for research or reference purposes (entry 1.13.1 and 1.13.2).</Item></List></Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Additional entries have been included to cover agreements, summary records of approvals, investigations into compliance breaches, findings of programs and projects and summary property information (entries 1.2.1, 1.2.2, 1.2.3, 1.3.1, 1.5.1, 1.9.1 and 1.10.1)</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Records identified for retention as State archives include records documenting:<List><Item>the development of high level strategies and plans for resource management (entry 1.16.1)</Item><Item>agreements to manage or maintain Crown lands (entry 1.2.1)</Item><Item>summary records of issued approvals, licences or permits, including approvals relating to forestry activities and the clearing of native vegetation or land (entry 1.3.1)</Item><Item>investigations into significant breaches of compliance and outbreaks of pests or diseases (entry 1.5.1, 1.17.1 and 1.18.1)</Item><Item>reports of findings of research and other significant programs and projects (entries 1.9.1 and 1.13.1)</Item><Item>summary records of livestock identification codes, brands or marks (entry 1.15.1)</Item><Item>unique data relating to natural resources and land use (entry 1.13.1 and 1.14.1).</Item></List></Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>These are in addition to minutes and papers of the Statewide and regional LLS Boards that are required as State archives under the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records</Source> (GA28). State policies on animal welfare, biosecurity, and natural resource management are also required as State archives under <Source>Functional retention and disposal authority: Primary industries assistance, regulation and development </Source>(FA258).</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Records covering routine operational processes and activities are proposed to be retained for minimum retention periods ranging from until administrative or reference use ceases to 75 years after action completed.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>LLS will also be using the relevant parts of <Source>Functional retention and disposal authority: Primary industries assistance, regulation and development </Source>(FA258)<Source> </Source>to cover drought and emergency response, education and training.  </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>LLS advised the nominated minimum retention periods and disposal actions meet current legal and statutory obligations and the administrative requirements of the organisation.</Paragraph>
    </ContextContent>
  </Context>
  <Term type="function" itemno="1.0.0">
    <TermTitle>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitle>
    <TermDescription>
      <Paragraph>The function of developing, administering, delivering and/or funding programs and advisory services associated with agricultural production, animal health and welfare, chemical residues, biosecurity, natural resource management and emergency management.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Note: Where the organisation is responsible for the management of Crown reserves, commons and land that are currently or may potentially be the subject of a claim under the Aboriginal Land Rights Act 1983, the organisation should ensure records providing evidence of ownership, control and usage of the relevant parcel are retained and not destroyed until a claim has been granted over that parcel of land.
These records could include planning documents or decisions concerning proposed or approved use of the land, surveys, agreements, memorandums, consents, tenure arrangements regarding the following land matters 
Please note that the making of a claim which is unsuccessful does not preclude the making of further claims over the same areas of land under the Act.
For further advice and guidance as to land that is claimable under the Aboriginal Land Rights Act and records requiring retention, agencies should contact the Crown Lands division of the Department of Industry.
</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="FA">258</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Primary industries assistance, regulation and development</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>DROUGHT &amp; EMERGENCY RESPONSE</TermTitleRef>
        <ItemNoRef>5.0.0</ItemNoRef>
        <SeeText>or records relating to assistance and support provided by the organisation in response to droughts, natural disasters or other emergency situations.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="FA">258</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Primary industries assistance, regulation and development</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>EDUCATION &amp; TRAINING</TermTitleRef>
        <ItemNoRef>6.0.0</ItemNoRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the provision of formal education and training to registered or enrolled participants, such as formal training to external registrants in the use of pesticides, poisons or baiting products.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the formation, meetings and decisions of committees, task forces, working or advisory groups.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the provision of customer services (including customer service charters), donations and fundraising activities, community gratuitous competitions and awards, complaints about the organisation's services, and general ongoing liaison and correspondence with professional associations, community, industry or private sector groups etc. for the routine sharing of information, networking and ongoing relationship management.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>CONTRACTING-OUT</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the outsourcing of services.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to formal inquiries involving the organisation; the provision of advice to the Minister or government regarding the organisation's policies, procedures, functions, etc.; the preparation of annual reports; and submissions by the organisation on the development or review of legislation, regulation, proposals, statutory planning instruments, etc. made by other government organisations.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>INFORMATION MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Cases</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the requests by members of the public to access information held by the organisation.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PERSONNEL</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Employee service history</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for copies of individual qualifications, certificates of competency, statements of attainment, etc., where these relate to occupational health and safety training or are required by employees as part of employment conditions or to perform their duties.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Conservation</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>heritage and conservation assessments and registers, and programs and projects involving the remediation, restoration, rehabilitation (or other conservation) of property owned, managed or controlled by the organisation, including crown lands and reserves.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Maintenance</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the maintenance of property owned, managed or controlled by the organisation, including crown lands and reserves which are not part of a funded program, project or initiative, such as routine pest or weed control, fencing, mowing, minor repair of structures, etc.).</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to delegations of authority made by the agency; audits on the performance of the organisation's activities and operations; and joint ventures, partnerships or similar collaborative relationships with government or private bodies (including associations, societies, networks, industry or community groups, etc.).</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Compliance</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the organisation's compliance with mandatory or optional requirements.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
    </TermDescription>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.1.0">
      <TermTitle>Advisory &amp; Extension</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with providing advice and extension services to landholders, primary producers, managers, or the wider community.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="FA">258</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Primary industries assistance, regulation and development</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>EDUCATION &amp; TRAINING</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the provision of formal education and training to registered or enrolled participants, such as formal training to external registrants in the use of pesticides, poisons or baiting products.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Celebrations, ceremonies, functions</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to administrative arrangements for all celebrations, ceremonies and functions, including arrangements for exhibition launches and the giving of addresses, etc.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Customer service</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to bookings for events.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Enquiries</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the handling of enquiries regarding routine information about the organisation and its services.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>COMMUNITY RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Marketing</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the marketing of exhibitions, field days, tours or other events held for the purpose of providing advice and information on local land issues and matters.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>EQUIPMENT &amp; STORES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Leasing-out</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the loan of learning materials and resources to schools, landholders or other stakeholders.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.1.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records documenting:<List><Item>final versions of information and advisory materials and resources. Includes fact sheets, newsletters, guides, resource kits, videos, general advisory information on the website, education and awareness materials for field days, tours, forums, school programs etc.</Item><Item>public meetings and reports on the outcomes of support groups, seminars, field days, etc.</Item><Item>advice and assistance where a formal response is provided. Includes diaries and notes which record landholder issues, observations, advice and recommendations made during site visits by field staff.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for field staff diaries (GDA20, entry 2.2.1) reduced from 10 to 7 years after action completed for consistency with similar records in the functional retention and disposal authority for primary industries (FA258, entries 1.3.1 and 2.5.1). 7 years meets accountability and business needs in case of potential claims regarding the validity and/or accuracy of advice and ensures the agency has a history of a particular property.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for advice to stakeholders increased from between 5 and 6 years (GDA20, entries 2.1.2 and 5.1.2, and GA29, entry 1.1.1) to 7 years after action completed and disposal action for final versions of information and advisory materials (GA29, entry 1.1.2) changed from retain until superseded or no longer required for reference purposes to 7 years after action completed to establish consistent retention periods for records of advice, including associated information resources and advisory materials.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.1.2 - change from retain until superseded or no longer required for reference to 7 years after action completed</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 2.2.1 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.1.1 - increase from 5 to 7 years</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 2.1.2 - increase from 6 to 7 years</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.1.2 6 years</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.1.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the development of advisory, education and information materials and resources.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalTrigger>administrative or reference use ceases</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for records relating to the development of resources (GA29, entry 1.1.3).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.1.3 - no change</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.2.0">
      <TermTitle>Agreements</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with negotiating, establishing, managing and reviewing agreements.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Authorisation &amp; Certification</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to authorisations to carry out controlled activities which may be in the form of an agreement such as grazing agreements/permits.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Grants &amp; Funding</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the establishment and management of specific funding agreements.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Programs, Projects &amp; Initiatives</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the establishment and management of agreements with landowners, managers or other stakeholders relating to specific programs, projects and initiatives.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to inter-agency committees, taskforces and working groups set up to manage negotiations for agreements.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>CONTRACTING-OUT</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to agreements and contracts for outsourced services.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Agreements</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the establishment and management of agreements with other government organisations.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Joint ventures</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the establishment and monitoring of significant strategic alliances with other organisations (government or non-government) regarding the core functional activities of the organisation.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <LinkedTo type="GDA20">3.1.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
      <Class itemno="1.2.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the negotiation, establishment and ongoing management of agreements with private landholders or other third parties to manage or maintain Crown lands owned, controlled or managed by the organisation. This includes memorandums of understanding, management, stewardship, conservation or similar agreements.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Retention as State archives consistent with equivalent records in the <Source>Functional retention and disposal authority: Crown lands management</Source> (FA253, entry 2.3.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">New entry</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 3 (2001)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.2.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to assistance provided by the organisation in the negotiation and establishment of agreements relating to land use and access, where the organisation is not the lead negotiator.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>agreements are approved and signed by all parties</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Retention period encompasses limitation periods for potential legal action or disputes concerning advice provided. </Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">New entry</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.2.3">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the negotiation, establishment, management and review of agreements that do not relate to the management or maintenance of Crown lands. Includes stewardship or conservation agreements. </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph><Emphasis>Note:</Emphasis> Statutory limitation periods for commencing a claim or action for breach of a contract or agreement may vary depending on the type of agreement or contract. For example longer time periods apply to deeds, specialty contracts and certain interstate agreements. Where longer limitation periods do apply these need to be taken into account when assessing retention requirements beyond the minimum period specified. </Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>expiry or termination of agreement</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Retention period encompasses limitation periods for potential legal action or disputes concerning fulfilment or terms and conditions of agreement.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">New entry</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.3.0">
      <TermTitle>Authorisation &amp; Certification</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with receiving and handling requests by external parties for authorisation to carry out a controlled activity, for certification relating to properties and stock, or compliance regarding a proposed controlled activity.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>(Advisory) for records relating to the establishment, meetings and outcomes of independent decision-making panels.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Accounting</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the receipt and processing of fees and refunds associated with permits or other approvals.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Compliance</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the organisation's seeking of authorisation to carry out a controlled activity, including (for example) licences and authorisation relating to the organisation's use of firearms, or consents sought from other organisations to fell or dispose of timber.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.3.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Summary records of approvals issued by the organisation, including licences and permits related to forestry, clearing of vegetation and native flora and fauna.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>New entry. State archives decision is consistent with equivalent records in the Functional retention and disposal authority for the Office of Environment and Heritage (FA314, entry 6.1.1) and the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: local Government records</Source> for registers documenting matters of long term environment concern (GA39, entry 11.10.1).</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Records document the impact of government and land use activities on the environment.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">New entry</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.3.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the receipt of applications for the <Emphasis>management or clearing of native vegetation or authorisation of private native forestry operations</Emphasis>. Includes:<List><Item>applications and supporting documentation</Item><Item>liaison with applicants or other stakeholders</Item><Item>assessments and due diligence checks</Item><Item>notifications, certifications and approvals</Item><Item>notifications of any cancellation, suspension, variation or revocation of an authorisation</Item><Item>records of any associated appeals.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Includes notifications received (and any associated withdrawals) of intentions to clear native vegetation. Includes approved and refused applications.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalCondition>If granted</DisposalCondition>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">20</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>cancellation, lapse, withdrawal, or other expiry or termination of authorisation, certification or notification</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalCondition>If refused</DisposalCondition>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">20</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for authorisations for vegetation clearing increased from 10 years after plan expires (GA29, entry 1.2.1) to 20 years after cancellation, withdrawal, lapse etc. Retention period meets long-term business and accountability needs to identify where a logging operation or vegetation clearing occurred. Summary information will be retained as State archives as information documenting the extent of clearing of native vegetation and/or land use activities over time is of ongoing value/use for research purposes.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="index">certification (native vegetation clearing)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="index">forestry approvals</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="index">logging approvals</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.2.1 increase from 10 to 20 years</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.16.1</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.3.3">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to applications or requests for a licence, permit, consent or other approval/authorisation and/or exemption concerning a controlled activity (excluding those relating to the clearing and management of native vegetation or private native forestry operations)<Emphasis>.</Emphasis> Includes:<List><Item>applications and supporting documentation</Item><Item>liaison with applicants or other stakeholders</Item><Item>assessments and due diligence checks</Item><Item>determinations and notifications</Item><Item>notifications of any cancellation, suspension, variation or revocation of a permit, consent, authorisation, certifications, exemption etc.</Item><Item>records of any associated appeals, including applications for compensations payable (as a result of the appeal) by the organisation.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Includes applications and requests which are subsequently refused.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalCondition>If granted</DisposalCondition>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>expiry, lapse or other termination of authorisation</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalCondition>If refused</DisposalCondition>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for Travelling Stock Reserve permits (GDA20, entry 5.4.1) increased from 6 to 7 years after expiry of permit for successful applications (GDA20 entry 5.4.1) and for unsuccessful permits from 1 to 7 years after action completed.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the authorisation or approval of encroachments on Crown land, including travelling stock reserves, are required to be retained in agency under the functional retention and disposal authority for Crown Lands (FA258, entry 1.4.7). Local Land Services have advised that records relating to usage of Crown land, such as Travelling Stock Reserves permits, that are currently or may potentially be the subject of a claim under the Aboriginal Land Rights Act 1983, will be retained and not destroyed until a claim has been granted over that parcel of land. </Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.4.1 - increase from 6 to 7 years</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.4.2 - increase from 1 to 7 years</LinkedTo>
        <Comment author="SRNSW">
          <Paragraph>For the moment prefer to leave TSR records as retain in agency. If the situation changes and upon advice from Crown Lands the authority can be amended.</Paragraph>
        </Comment>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.3.4">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to requests for the provision of health or residue certification for properties and/or stock, such as those required for the export of stock, movement of stock interstate, or property searches.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for records relating to health or residue certification (GDA20, entry 2.3.1) increased from 6 to 7 years after action completed to streamline the authority. Retention period is consistent with equivalent records in the functional retention and disposal authority for Primary Industries (FA258, entry 2.1.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 2.3.1 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="index">property search requests</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.4.0">
      <TermTitle>Board Elections</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity of managing elections for board members</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>GOVERNING BODIES</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for all other records relating to the management of Boards, including appointments, nominations, registers of Board members and pecuniary interest, Board meetings, arrangements for and payments made to Board members (e.g. travel), Board policies and procedures, delegations to members, audits of governance practices, etc.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.4.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the conduct of elections for members to local Boards.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <CustomAction>
            <Paragraph>Retain in accordance with relevant legislative or regulatory requirements for the conduct of elections, or for a minimum of 1 year after action completed, then destroy</Paragraph>
          </CustomAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Disposal action amended to enable destruction of records in accordance with the <Source>Local Land Services Regulation 2014</Source> which requires the destruction of marked and any unmarked ballot papers, the roll and other papers or envelopes used in the election to be destroyed after 12 months (Schedule 1, clause 51). Minimum retention period for nomination forms, ballot papers, etc., reduced from 6 years after action completed (GDA20, entry 3.4.2), to 1 year after completion of election for compliance with the <Source>Local Land Services Regulation 2014</Source> which requires the destruction of marked and any unmarked ballot papers, the roll and other papers or envelopes used in the election to be destroyed after 12 months.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.4.2 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="mandate">Local Land Services Regulation 2014 Schedule 1, clause 51</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.5.0">
      <TermTitle>Compliance Monitoring &amp; Enforcement</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated monitoring compliance with legislation, regulations, rules or other requirements, and taking necessary enforcement actions either in response to identified breaches, or as deemed necessary to ensure the protection and preservation of the environment and agricultural production.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>LEGAL SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Litigation</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to legal proceedings between the organisation and other parties in a court or other tribunal.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Compliance</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the organisation's compliance with mandatory or optional requirements.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">8</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Video/visual surveillance records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for audio or video surveillance recordings that are not of evidentiary value, or required as part of an investigation.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Comment author="SRNSW">
        <Paragraph>1.6.4 removed.</Paragraph>
      </Comment>
      <Class itemno="1.5.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records documenting investigations into and the outcomes of compliance breaches that:<List><Item>set a precedent</Item><Item>result in substantial changes to the organisation's policies, procedures or processes, or</Item><Item>pose major issues at a state or regional level for environmental conservation, land management, animal health and welfare, biosecurity or public health and safety.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Includes inspection notes, photographs and reports on the findings and outcomes of investigations, legal advice, enforcement actions taken, and records of appeals made.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>New entry. Retention of investigations into compliance breaches that set a precedent etc. as State archives is consistent with equivalent records in the functional retention and disposal authority for Crown Lands (FA253, entry 5.2.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">New entry</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 2 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.5.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the routine operational monitoring and enforcement of compliance with requirements as set out in laws, regulations, codes, standards etc. Records include:<List><Item>periodic compliance reports, returns (e.g. annual returns) and notifications</Item><Item>field officers notebooks and diaries</Item><Item>complaints or reports of identified breaches</Item><Item>photographs and reports detailing the outcome of inspections, audits or other monitoring activities</Item><Item>notes of meetings and liaison with landholders or other stakeholder</Item><Item>notices of entry or inspection issued to occupiers of premises</Item><Item>notices, directions or orders issued</Item><Item>records relating to compensations payable</Item><Item>appeals, including to tribunals, courts or other higher authorities.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for monitoring and enforcement of compliance increased from 6 years (GDA20, entries 4.3.1 and 5.3.1) to 7 years to streamline the authority and for consistency with equivalent records of infringements held by Crown Lands (FA253, entry 5.1.1), and the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: local government records</Source> (GA39, entries 19.6.1 and 11.3.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.3.1 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.3.1 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.5.3">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the issue of orders, notices or directions which prohibit, restrict, suspend or direct certain activities or operations. Includes:<List><Item>orders, notices and directions issued by the organisation</Item><Item>maps or plans showing prohibited or restricted zones</Item><Item>liaison with land owners and occupiers or other stakeholders</Item><Item>records relating requests for and the recovery of any associated costs</Item><Item>appeals, including to higher authorities.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Also includes recommendations and proposals to the Minister to issue orders.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for the issue of orders, notices etc increased from 6 years (GDA20, entries 4.1.2 and 5.3.1) to 7 years after action completed to streamline the authority.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.1.2 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.3.1 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.6.0" update="2025-03-12">
      <TermTitle>Grants &amp; Funding</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with administering grants, funds, incentives or other financial assistance to landholders, primary producers, community groups, non-government organisations or other stakeholders.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>See General Retention and Disposal Authority <Source>Administrative records</Source> <Emphasis>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT – Grant funding</Emphasis> and allocation for records relating to administration of grants and subsidies.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Agreements</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the establishment and management of management agreements (or similar)with bodies, groups or individuals for the purposes of ensuring the ongoing support and maintenance of outcomes from funded activities.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Programs, Projects &amp; Initiatives</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to establishment, administration, monitoring, evaluation and review of funded programs and projects.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Joint ventures</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to joint ventures and similar collaborative arrangements with funding partners (investors).</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.6.1" update="2025-03-12">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Superseded - see general retention and disposal authority: administrative records (GA28 19.8.6)</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for funding of natural resource management projects in catchment areas (GA29, 1.5.2) reduced from 10 to 7 years after action completed for consistency with similar records in the functional retention and disposal authorities for Primary Industries (FA258, entry 2.6.1).</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for grants to improve travelling stock reserves increased from 6 to 7 years to streamline the authority.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.5.2 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.2.2 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
        <Comment author="SRNSW">
          <Paragraph>Previous entry</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to successful applications for grants and funding. Includes:<List><Item>expressions of interest, applications and supporting documentation</Item><Item>internal assessments and recommendations</Item><Item>advice of application outcomes</Item><Item>ongoing liaison and correspondence with recipients</Item><Item>establishment and ongoing management of funding contracts and agreements</Item><Item>progress updates, periodic financial returns and acquittal reports from fund recipients.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Note: Statutory limitation periods for commencing a claim or action for breach of a contract or agreement may vary depending on the type of agreement or contract. For example longer time periods apply to deeds, specialty contracts and certain interstate agreements. Where longer limitation periods do apply these need to be taken into account when assessing retention requirements beyond the minimum period specified.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Retain 7 years after action completed, then destroy</Paragraph>
        </Comment>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.6.2" update="2025-03-12">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Superseded - see general retention and disposal authority: administrative records (GA28 19.8.7)</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for unsuccessful applications for funding (GA29, entry 1.5.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.5.1 (2 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.2.3 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
        <Comment author="SRNSW">
          <Paragraph>Previous entry</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to unsuccessful applications for grants and funding. Includes:<List><Item>expressions of interest, applications and supporting documentation</Item><Item>internal assessments and recommendations</Item><Item>advice of application outcomes</Item><Item>ongoing liaison and correspondence with recipients</Item><Item>progress updates, periodic financial returns and acquittal reports from fund recipients.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Retain minimum 2 years after action completed, then destroy</Paragraph>
        </Comment>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.7.0">
      <TermTitle>Incidents</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with responding to local incidents where the organisation is the primary government responding agency for agriculture and animal services.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="FA">258</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Primary industries assistance, regulation and development</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>DROUGHT &amp; EMERGENCY RESPONSE</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to assistance and support provided by the organisation in response to droughts, natural disasters or other emergency situations.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.7.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to support and assistance provided by the organisation in the handling of specific local incidents such as livestock transport accidents or pest infestations where landholders are unable to effectively manage control operations. Records include:<List><Item>liaison with landholders, site controllers, emergency or other agencies, as required</Item><Item>photographs, notes and evidence gathered, and immediate actions taken at the incident site</Item><Item>incident reports.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for records relating to assistance provided with disease control increased from 6 to 7 years to streamline the authority, and to ensure that records are available for a sufficient period of time in the event of any claims with regard to the organisation's handling of an incident.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.8.0">
      <TermTitle>Policies &amp; Procedures</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity of developing and reviewing policies and procedures, including rules, principles, guidelines, instructions, manuals etc.</Paragraph>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.8.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Final versions of policies or procedures relating to local land service services, operations and activities.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>superseded, withdrawn from use or action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Consistent with retention periods applying to policies and procedures for natural resource management in catchment areas (GA29, 1.9.1). Statewide strategic policies on core functions of the Rural Lands Protection Board are identified as State archives under GDA20, entry 3.6.1. However, these policies and procedures are informed by State policies on animal welfare, biosecurity, and natural resource management which are developed by the Department of Industry and will be retained as State archives under the functional retention and disposal authority for primary industries (FA258, entries 1.7.1, 2.9.1, and 10.10.1). Local Land Services policies include the compliance and enforcement policy, truck rollover policy, policy on the emergency use of travelling stock reserves and the wild dog policy.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.9.1 (7 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.6.2 (until superseded)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.6.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.8.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the development and review of policies, procedures, guidelines, manuals etc. such as drafts distributed for review, stakeholder feedback and comments, supporting papers and working documents etc.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalTrigger>administrative or reference use ceases</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for development and review of policies and procedures (GA29, entry 1.9.2 and GDA20, entry 3.6.2).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.6.2 (until superseded)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.9.2 (reference ceases)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.9.0">
      <TermTitle>Programs, Projects &amp; Initiatives</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>Records relating to the establishment, development, implementation and review of on-ground programs and projects to address identified issues and priorities within regions or across the state.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>This may include programs and projects which (for example) aim to:<List><Item>eradicate, control or reduce threats to the environment or primary production, such as pest and weed pest control programs;</Item><Item>monitor, protect, rehabilitate or restore natural resources (e.g. water, soils, vegetation or ecosystems);</Item><Item>improve primary production outcomes and profitability.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><Emphasis>Note: </Emphasis>Excludes programs and projects involving the remediation, restoration, rehabilitation (or other conservation) of Crown land or reserves, or the removal of hazardous or toxic substances on Crown land or reserves where the land is either owned, controlled or managed by the organisation.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Advisory &amp; Extension</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to advice provided to landholders unrelated to a specific program or project, for example advice and recommendations provided to landholders regarding pest control, conservation measures etc.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Authorisation &amp; Certification</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the issue of specific licences, permits, consents or other authorisations associated with the implementation of a program or project.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Compliance Monitoring &amp; Enforcement</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to monitoring compliance and taking enforcement actions (where necessary) for breaches of compliance identified as part of any program or project implementation.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Grants &amp; Funding</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the administration of grants and funding to landholders, community groups, organisations or other groups or individuals for programs, projects and initiatives.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Property Summary Information</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for summarised information held in relation to a property, including a summary of pesticides, poisons or other chemicals issued to landholders.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Strategy &amp; Planning</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the development of state, regional or local plans from which specific programs and projects may result (e.g. State, regional or local weed or pest control plans).</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Conservation</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for programs and projects involving the remediation, restoration, rehabilitation (or other conservation) of Crown Lands or reserves owned, controlled or managed by the organisation.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.9.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Final reports and findings of programs and projects that are:<List><Item>considered a unique and/or valuable intelligence source in identifying issues, patterns, trends, etc. impacting land, primary production or natural resources over time</Item><Item>used to inform major changes to policies, practices, services or operations.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Records document the impact of government activities on the environment.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 2 (2001)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 2 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.9.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the establishment, development, implementation and review of programs and projects, initiatives or campaigns, including:<List><Item>final program and project plans, reports, schedules, objectives, methodologies, communication plans, etc.</Item><Item>records of program or project steering committees</Item><Item>establishment and management of agreements and arrangements with parties participating in the program or project, including ongoing management agreements</Item><Item>consultation and liaison with partners, landholders or other stakeholders</Item><Item>final versions of factsheets, technical guidelines or other information resources.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph><Emphasis>Note</Emphasis>: Where programs and projects involve the establishment of management agreements (which extend beyond the life of the program or project), records should be retained for 7 years after the expiry, lapse or termination of that agreement.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for records relating to the establishment of catchment area programs (GA29, entry 1.10.1) reduced from 10 to 7 years after action completed, and for pest control programs increased from 6 to 7 years to streamline the authority. The agency has confirmed that 7 years meets their business and accountability needs. </Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.10.1 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.10.2 (5 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.10.3 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.2.2 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.2.3 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.13.1 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.9.3">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the development of final program or project documentation (reports, plans, information resources, etc.), including:<List><Item>drafts</Item><Item>routine internal liaison and meetings</Item><Item>supporting background and working documents, etc.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">3</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Records are operational in nature and likely to have limited ongoing use for administrative, accountability or reference purposes.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.11.2 (reference ceases)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term itemno="1.10.0">
      <TermTitle>Property Summary Information</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with summary information relating to individual properties.</Paragraph>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.10.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to key property information (either for private or public land) which provides a summarised history of activities and operations carried out on, or issues impacting individual properties. Specifically this includes summarised information which identifies:<List><Item>diseases, chemical spills, contaminants or other potential long term biosecurity issues impacting the property</Item><Item>pesticides, poisons or other chemical products issued for and used on the property (including what was issued, when and for what purpose)</Item><Item>compliance breaches and enforcement actions where these relate to activities adversely affecting the property</Item><Item>orders issued relating to the land.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">75</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>New entry. Minimum retention period meets long term reference needs for information on chemical residues and livestock diseases such as anthrax which have the ability to affect land production for decades, and to support property search requests where the agency needs information on any activities that might adversely affect the property, or orders issued on the land. </Paragraph>
        </Justification>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.11.0">
      <TermTitle>Rates, Levies, Fees &amp; Contributions</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with making and imposing rates, levies or contributions on rateable or other land, and fees and charges for services.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Note: Includes animal health rates for rateable land, catchment contributions, and any other special purpose rates as determined by the agency (e.g. for pest management).</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Agreements</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to agreements with Councils, statutory authorities and corporations or other local agencies to make assessments and reassessments, determine contributions, or collect rates, levies and contributions on behalf of the agency.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Compliance Monitoring &amp; Enforcement</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the sale of land for the purposes of recovering unpaid rates, levies or other charges. Including where the sale did not proceed.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Accounting</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for collecting, processing and recording the payment of rates, levies and contributions, including debt recovery activities.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Policy</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the setting of fees and charges.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.11.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Rate books, registers or other summary record of ratepayers.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for summary records of ratepayers (GDA20, entry 3.7.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.7.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.11.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the calculation, determination and administration of rates, levies and contributions, including:<List><Item>annual returns (of land and stock)</Item><Item>assessments of notional carrying capacity of land or catchment contributions, including notices of assessments and applications for review</Item><Item>calculations and estimates (e.g. of income and expenditure)</Item><Item>liaison with land owners or occupiers, including notices received regarding changes of occupancy or ownership of rateable land, or changes of address details</Item><Item>determinations, certificates and/or notices outlining amounts due</Item><Item>Ministerial approvals relating the collection of monies on behalf of the agency</Item><Item>records of waivers, deferrals or exemptions granted</Item><Item>summons for the recovery of rates and solicitor's enquiries regarding outstanding rates</Item><Item>records of appeals made.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for records relating to calculation of rates (GDA20, entry 3.7.2) increased from 6 to 7 years to streamline the authority.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.7.2 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.11.3">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to:<List><Item>routine enquiries about rates, levies, fees or other charges; and</Item><Item>applications and requests for waivers, deferrals or exemptions of rates, levies, fees or other charges which are not granted by the organisation.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">2</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for routine enquires (GDA20, entry 3.7.3) reduced from 3 to 2 years to streamline the authority and for consistency with similar records in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: local government records </Source>(GA39, entries 25.6.2 &amp; 2.8.2).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.7.3 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.11.4">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to requests to reissue rate notices.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="months">6</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for request to reissue rate notices in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: local government records</Source> (GA39, entry 25.5.3).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.11.5">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the sale of land for the purposes of recovering unpaid rates, levies or other debts owing to the organisation, including where the sale did not subsequently proceed. Includes:<List><Item>arrangements for and notices of sale</Item><Item>results of searches investigations to ascertain the identity of any person who has an interest in the land</Item><Item>records of public auctions held.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for debt recovery records in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: local government records</Source> (GA39, entry 25.5.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term itemno="1.12.0" type="activity">
      <TermTitle>Reporting</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with preparing reports and/or statistics in response to a specific request, or which summarise specific activities and operations.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Note: Use the relevant activity for reports generated in relation to a specific activity. For example, see <Emphasis>Research</Emphasis> for research reports, or <Emphasis>Programs, Projects &amp; Initiatives</Emphasis> for reports on the progress, outcomes or review of specific programs, programs and initiatives managed or coordinated by the organisation.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Reporting</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for reports to government or cabinet relating to the organisation's functions, activities and/or performance.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.12.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Final versions of high-level formal reports prepared by the organisation which provide comprehensive information to government or other key stakeholders in relation to regulated activities, the state of, or issues impacting the environment, or specific issues as directed by legislation or policy.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for reports to Government relating to the organisation's core functions and performance in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records </Source>(GA28, entry 10.11.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 2 (2001)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.12.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating:<List><Item>informal reports and updates to internal or external stakeholders, or routine statistics relating to routine operational or administrative matters;</Item><Item>submissions to government environment (or similar) reports, where the organisation is not the NSW lead agency; and</Item><Item>records relating to the compilation of reports to internal or external stakeholders.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">3</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for periodic reports to external government organisations regarding programs and services in the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records</Source> (GA28, entry 10.11.3). </Paragraph>
        </Justification>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.13.0">
      <TermTitle>Research &amp; Surveys</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with carrying out research, surveys, studies, or similar inquiries in order to discover facts, confirm or enhance knowledge etc.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Programs, Projects &amp; Initiatives</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to surveys or research as an output of programs and projects funded by the organisation.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.13.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Final reports, papers and findings of research conducted or commissioned by the organisation. Includes datasets considered unique and valuable in supporting longitudinal studies or monitoring of natural resource issues, activities, patterns or trends.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for final reports of original research into natural resources management (GA29, entries 1.7.1 and 1.12.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.12.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.7.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.7.2 (retain in agency)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 2 (2001)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.13.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the conduct of research, surveys and studies carried out or commissioned by the organisation, including:<List><Item>survey or questionnaire templates and completed surveys or questionnaire results</Item><Item>results of interviews</Item><Item>observation, monitoring or other data sets used to support research.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalTrigger>no longer required for reference or research purposes</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Disposal action changed from retain in agency or for between 5 to 7 years after action completed (GA29, entries 1.7.2, 1.12.2, 1.12.3) to retain until no longer required for reference or research purposes. </Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.12.2 (7 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.12.3 (5 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.12.4 (1 year)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.7.2 (retain in agency)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.13.3">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to abandoned or discontinued research, studies or surveys.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">3</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>New entry. The proposed retention period ensures a minimum period of reference in the event that abandoned or discontinued research is revisited.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.14.0">
      <TermTitle>Spatial Information</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with gathering, recording and managing spatial data and information to support the organisation’s land management activities and operations.</Paragraph>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.14.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Spatial data gathered through the conduct of the organisation's activities which is used to identify, plan, map, monitor and report on activities and works carried out on land that is unique and/or cannot be readily recreated and supports longitudinal research re patterns and impacts of land use.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Includes original maps and plans produced or commissioned by the organisation (including by predecessor agencies) where the spatial data does not otherwise exist to enable these to be reproduced.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for original maps and plans that support natural resource management (GA29, entry 1.14.2). Data provides evidence of activities on land within a region, e.g. land clearing, tree planting or condition of land condition over time.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.14.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Spatial data gathered through the conduct of the organisation's activities which is not unique and can be readily recreated.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalTrigger>superseded or no longer required for ongoing reference</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Retention period based on potential use of records for reference and research purposes. Unique data is being retained as State archives (see entry above).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.15.0">
      <TermTitle>Stock Identification</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with managing and/or administering schemes for the identification of stock in NSW.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Advisory &amp; Extension</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for general information and advice (including in the form of factsheets, frequently asked questions, handbooks, guides etc.) provided to land owners or occupiers in relation to stock identification or related matters.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Authorisation &amp; Certification</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the requests and approvals provided by the agency to use special stock identifiers (e.g. special brands for pigs).</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Compliance Monitoring &amp; Enforcement</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to monitoring and enforcing compliance with stock identification requirements.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Rates, Levies, Fees &amp; Contributions</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the determination of levies and fees associated with the stock identification schemes.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Comment author="agency">
        <Paragraph>
          <Emphasis>Source</Emphasis>
          <List>
            <Item><Source url="https://www.dpi.nsw.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0006/723633/Procedures-for-assigning-property-identification-codes-and-for-managing-and-accessing-registers.pdf">Procedures and responsibilities for assigning property identification codes </Source>(DPI procedure)</Item>
            <Item>LLS Website: <Source url="https://www.lls.nsw.gov.au/livestock/stock-identification">stock identification</Source></Item>
            <Item><Source url="file:///C:/Users/ruth/Downloads/RLPB_State_Council_stockIDsystem.pdf">State Council Stock Identification System</Source> (Rural Lands Protection Board)</Item>
            <Item>Noted that LLS maintain the District register of PICs</Item>
            <Item>Identification codes are recorded by each LLS (District register), provided to NSW DPI for collation (State register), then uploaded from the State register to the NLIS database. </Item>
            <Item>An identification code remains active for three years or for a shorter period specified in writing by the district registrar.</Item>
            <Item>Biosecurity (National Livestock Identification System) Regulation 2017</Item>
          </List>
        </Paragraph>
      </Comment>
      <Class itemno="1.15.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Registers of stock identification codes, brands or marks.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for livestock registers (GDA20, entry 5.1.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.1.1 Required as State archives</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 3 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.15.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the management and/or administration of schemes for the identification of stock, such as those relating to property identification codes, brands, earmarks or tattoos. Includes:<List><Item>the receipt and processing of applications for and the assignment of codes, brands or marks, including renewals</Item><Item>applications or notifications from land owners/occupiers regarding changes to contact details</Item><Item>records relating to their ongoing management, such as requests to transfer brands or marks, or amalgamate properties within a single code, or records relating to the suspension, blocking reactivation or cancellation of identifiers</Item><Item>local registers of identification codes, brands or marks (e.g. District Registers).</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Disposal action changed from retain until identification system ceases being used, then destroy, to retain a minimum of 7 years after action completed. The <Source>Biosecurity (National Livestock Identification System) Regulation 2017</Source> requires information relating to stock identification to be retained for a minimum of 7 years. Identification codes typically remain active for only 3 years. Identification codes typically remain active for only 3 years. Registers of stock identification codes, brands or marks are required as State archives (entry 1.15.1 above).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.1.2 retain until identification system ceases</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.16.0">
      <TermTitle>Strategy &amp; Planning</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with developing and reviewing plans and strategies formulated to achieve goals and objectives.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Advisory &amp; Extension</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to advice and assistance to landholders (through workshops, meetings, discussions etc.) to develop plans relating to their properties (e.g. biosecurity plans or farm plans).</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Programs, Projects &amp; Initiatives</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the development of plans relating to an individual program, project or initiative.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>COMMITTEES</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the formulation and meetings of committees, taskforces or similar working groups set up for strategic planning purposes.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Comment author="agency">
        <Paragraph>
          <Emphasis>Source</Emphasis>
          <List>
            <Item>LLS Act 2013, Part 4, Division 1 and 2, identifying requirements for State and local land services plans; and LLS website for other plans (weed management, pest animal management plans,TSR planning framework etc.)</Item>
          </List>
        </Paragraph>
      </Comment>
      <Class itemno="1.16.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the development and review of high level strategies and plans which:<List><Item>set the overarching priorities, strategies and framework for the delivery and management of local land services;</Item><Item>reflect a co-ordinated and co-operative approach across government, industry and community to achieving environmental outcomes, where the organisation is the lead; and/or</Item><Item>are subject to extensive public consultation and/or relating to matters which are considered significant or contentious.</Item></List></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Records include:<List><Item>Ministerial directions</Item><Item>terms of reference</Item><Item>major drafts released for comment</Item><Item>notices of public consultations</Item><Item>results of public consultation, including submissions received</Item><Item>approvals</Item><Item>final versions of plans.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for strategic planning (GA29, entry 1.8.1 and GDA20 entry 2.4.1 and 5.2.1), and for primary industries (FA258, entries 1.6.1,2.8.1, 5.1.1, 10.9.1)</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.2 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.3 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 2.4.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.5.1 (until superseded)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.5.2 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.2.4 (until superseded)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 5.2.1 State archives</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 2 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.16.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to the development and review of routine local operational plans and strategies relating to the management of specific programs and activities, e.g. local pest control plans, investment strategies, etc. Includes:<List><Item>major drafts</Item><Item>records of consultations</Item><Item>final versions.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>superseded or action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Minimum retention period for community consultation over natural resource issues, investment strategies, strategic plans and implementation plans for specific natural resources (GA29, entries 1.3.1, 1.6.1, 1.8.5, 1.8.7), reduced from 10 to 7 years after action completed to streamline the authority. The agency has advised that the records are routine in nature and 7 years meets their business needs.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.5.1 (until superseded)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.3.1 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.6.1 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.6.2 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.5 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.6 (2 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.7 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.8 (2 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.4 (15 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.5.2 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.2.4 (until superseded)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.16.3">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Routine records relating to the development of all plans and strategies, such as:<List><Item>minor drafts for internal review</Item><Item>internal liaison and meetings</Item><Item>supporting background and working documents, etc.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">2</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for the development of natural resource strategic and implementation plans (GA29, entries 1.8.6 and 1.8.8). Minimum retention period for development of investment strategies and management plans (GDA20, entry 3.5.2 and GA29, entry 1.6.2) reduced from 3 years after approval to 2 years after action completed to streamline the authority.</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 3.5.2 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.6.2 (3 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.6 (2 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GA29 1.8.8 (2 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.2.4 (until superseded)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.17.0">
      <TermTitle>Surveillance &amp; Investigations (Biosecurity)</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with carrying out monitoring and surveillance of biosecurity threats, such as diseases, pests, weeds and contaminants, and conducting associated investigations.</Paragraph>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Advisory &amp; Extension</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the provision of advice to landholders, the community or other stakeholders regarding biosecurity matters.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Authorisation &amp; Certification</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to health or residue certification for properties and/or stock, including health certificates and crossing papers.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Compliance Monitoring &amp; Enforcement</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to monitoring compliance with requirements and the conduct of investigations in response to identified breaches.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Programs, Projects &amp; Initiatives</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the establishment and implementation of specific projects and programs (either carried out or coordinated by the organisation) to control or eradicate pests and weeds.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <TermTitleRef>LOCAL LAND SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>Property Summary Information</TermTitleRef>
          <SeeText>for summary records of diseases, contaminants or other biosecurity issues affecting individual properties.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
        <SeeReference>
          <IDRef control="FA">258</IDRef>
          <AuthorityTitleRef>Primary industries assistance, regulation and development</AuthorityTitleRef>
          <TermTitleRef>DROUGHT &amp; EMERGENCY RESPONSE</TermTitleRef>
          <ItemNoRef>5.0.0</ItemNoRef>
          <SeeText>for records relating to the planning, preparation and response to animal health and welfare matters during or following droughts or emergency events.</SeeText>
        </SeeReference>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.17.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating investigations following the diagnosis of disease or the identification of contaminants, pests or weeds where findings indicate potential or real high risk impacts to animal or human health, agricultural production or the environment. Includes:<List><Item>diaries or notes made by vets or other field officers during the course of investigations</Item><Item>photographs, results of interviews or other evidence gathered</Item><Item>notifications to responding or other agencies and organisations</Item><Item>reports on the outcomes of investigations.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for significant biosecurity investigations and records regarding the handling of significant emergency events in the functional retention and disposal authority for Primary Industries (FA258, entries 2.7.1 and 5.1.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
      <Class itemno="1.17.2">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating day-to-day monitoring and surveillance of diseases, contaminants, pests and weeds, including subsequent investigations where findings indicate low risk impacts to animal or human health, agricultural production or the environment. Includes:<List><Item>diaries or notes made by vets or other field offers recording observations, advice and recommendations made during site visits</Item><Item>requests for and results of tests to confirm the presence or absence of disease or contaminants</Item><Item>notifications or reports (to or from the organisation) of notifiable diseases, contamination, pests or weeds, etc.</Item><Item>photographs, information gathered to support investigations, and reports of investigation findings</Item><Item>liaison with external departments, bodies or individuals (as required)</Item></List></Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
          <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
          <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Reduces minimum retention period for ranger/veterinarian diaries from 10 to 7 years (GDA20, entry 2.2.1), and increases the retention period for monitoring of pest control by landholders (GDA20, entry 4.2.1) from 6 to 7 years to streamline the authority. </Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 2.2.1 (10 years)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 4.2.1 (6 years)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
    <Term type="activity" itemno="1.18.0">
      <TermTitle>Zoning</TermTitle>
      <TermDescription>
        <Paragraph>The activity associated with managing the classification of land in the local area.</Paragraph>
      </TermDescription>
      <Class itemno="1.18.1">
        <ClassDescription>
          <Paragraph>Records relating to applications for regional areas to hold the status of/be declared as biosecure areas (or similar health status). Includes European Union applications and declaration of protected or exclusion zones.</Paragraph>
        </ClassDescription>
        <Disposal>
          <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
        </Disposal>
        <Justification>
          <Paragraph>Confirms existing authorised disposal decision for animal health zoning (GDA20, entry 2.6.1).</Paragraph>
        </Justification>
        <LinkedTo type="linking table">GDA20 2.6.1 (State archives)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 2 (2001)</LinkedTo>
        <LinkedTo type="SRNSW appraisal objective">Objective 5 (2001)</LinkedTo>
      </Class>
    </Term>
  </Term>
</Authority>
