<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Authority xmlns="http://www.records.nsw.gov.au/schemas/RDA">
  <ID control="AR">567</ID>
  <ID control="SRFileNo">SR2024/61</ID>
  <ID control="FA">449</ID>
  <AuthorityTitle>Land and Environment Court of NSW</AuthorityTitle>
  <Scope>Land and Environment Court</Scope>
  <Status>
    <Draft version="1">
      <Agency agencyno="1120">Land and Environment Court</Agency>
      <Date>2024-07-24</Date>
    </Draft>
    <Submitted>
      <Officer>Sarah Froh</Officer>
      <Position>Director and Registrar</Position>
      <Agency agencyno="1120">Land and Environment Court</Agency>
      <Date>2024-10-15</Date>
    </Submitted>
    <Approved>2024-12-11</Approved>
    <Issued>
      <Agency agencyno="1120">Land and Environment Court</Agency>
      <Date>2025-01-10</Date>
    </Issued>
  </Status>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.3.2 - see GA28 19.16.2 change from retain until superseded to 3 years</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.14 - removed see GA28 for file control systems</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.9 - note added to main function description.</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.8 - note added to main function description</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.3.3 - removed</LinkedTo>
  <Context type="appraisal report">
    <ContextTitle>Background</ContextTitle>
    <ContextContent>
      <Paragraph>The Land and Environment Court of NSW was established in 1980 as a superior court of record. It has appellate and review jurisdiction in relation to planning, building, environmental, mining and ancillary matters. It also has summary criminal jurisdiction and appellate criminal jurisdiction in relation to environmental offences. The Court has judges and commissioners. The commissioners adjudicate, conciliate or mediate cases. The Court’s jurisdiction is divided into the following classes:</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 1: merits review of administrative decisions of local or State government under various planning or environmental laws. Class 1 represents approximately 61% of cases. Cases are usually heard by a commissioner but may also be referred to a judge. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 2: local government and miscellaneous appeals and applications in relation to tree disputes, local government approvals and orders, and strata scheme developments. These matters represent 8% of cases. Tree disputes are heard by a commissioner while other matters are heard by a judge or commissioners.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 3: land tenure, valuation, rating and compensation matters. This can include compensation for compulsory acquisition of land and land valuation objections. Valuation objections are usually heard by commissioners, compensation claims and Aboriginal land claims are usually heard by a judge. These proceedings constitute 9% of cases.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 4: environmental planning and protection, development contract and strata renewal plan civil enforcement and judicial review. Proceedings are heard by a judge and constitute 7.5% of cases. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 5: summary criminal enforcement proceedings, usually by government authorities prosecuting offences against planning or environmental laws. Prosecutions are heard by a judge without a jury, and constitute 14% of cases. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 6 and 7: criminal appeals from a lower court which are heard by a judge and constitute less than 1% of cases.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 8: civil proceedings under the Mining Act 1992 and the Petroleum (Onshore) Act 1991, which are heard by a Commissioner for Mining or a judge. Matters are less than 1% of cases.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 1, 2, 3, 4 or 8 appeals are to the NSW Court of Appeal. Class 5, 6 or 7 appeals are to the NSW Court of Criminal Appeal. Appeals from a decision of a commissioner in Class 1, 2, 3 or 8 are to a Judge of the Court and any further appeals from the Judge’s decision is only by leave of the NSW Court of Appeal. </Paragraph>
    </ContextContent>
  </Context>
  <Context type="appraisal report">
    <ContextTitle>Issue</ContextTitle>
    <ContextContent>
      <Paragraph>FA228 was issued in 2006 and has been revised by staff from the Court and State Records NSW. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Records covered by the <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records </Source>(GA28) have been removed. The number of entries has been reduced from 23 to 11, 45% of which are required as State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Below is a summary of proposed changes:</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Records	Change	Justification	Entry</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph><Emphasis>Class 1 case files (review of local or State government decisions under various planning or environmental laws)</Emphasis>. Required as State archives. Entry 1.2</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Change</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>1.	Removal of random sampling (first 500 cases heard from 1980) as a criterion to determine State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>2.	Removal of allowance for a sample of files (illustrative of significant changes to the Court's jurisdiction, practice and procedure, or the nature of the cases bought before it and their outcomes) to be transferred as State archives at the discretion of the Court. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>3.	Currently all cases heard by a judge are required as State archives. In addition to this it is proposed that cases heard by a commissioner that relate to developments that are a recipient of a State, national or international architectural or design award, are an important local or regional landmark, relate to heritage listed properties, are controversial or attract media interest will also be retained as State archives. (Previously development application cases heard by a commissioner were not required as State archives but were required to be retained by the Court).</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Justification</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>1. Random sampling is no longer seen as an appropriate method of determining State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>2.	Cases heard by a judge and the new requirement for significant cases heard by commissioners fulfill the State archives requirements without the need to retain an additional discretionary sample.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>3.	The Court advised that cases heard by commissioners can be as significant as those heard by judges. The criterion is consistent with that applying to building records in other disposal authorities. Examples of matters that attract controversy and media interest are “spite hedges”, and solar and wind farms.	1.2 </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph><Emphasis>Class 1 case files (review of local or State government decisions under various planning or environmental laws).  Retain minimum of 12 years after commencement of matter</Emphasis>. Entry 1.3</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Change</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Confirms existing decision for matters other than development applications. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Previously development application matters heard by a commissioner were required to be retained by the Court (i.e. no approval to destroy). It is now proposed that development applications will be retained as State archives under entry 1.2, or 12 years after the commencement of the matter under entry 1.3.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>The Court is not the consent authority. Records of these developments that are created and managed by the consent authority (usually a local council or the NSW Planning) are required as State archives if they meet the criteria, or for at least 7 years after the structure is demolished. The Court has no business need to retain these files on an ongoing basis. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Summary records of all Court matters will be retained as State archives under entry 1.1. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph><Emphasis>Class 2 case files (tree disputes, local government approvals and orders, and strata scheme developments). Required as State archives</Emphasis>. Entry 1.4</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Change</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>1.	Removal of random sampling (first 500 cases heard from 1980) as a criterion to determine State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>2.	Removal of allowance for a sample of files (illustrative of significant changes to the Court's jurisdiction, practice and procedure, or the nature of the cases bought before it and their outcomes) at the discretion of the Court. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>3.	Currently all cases heard by a judge are required as State archives. In addition to this it is proposed that cases heard by a commissioner that relate to heritage listed trees or are controversial and attract media interest will also be retained as State archives.	</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Justification</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>1.	Random sampling is no longer seen as an appropriate method of determining State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>2.	Cases heard by a judge and the new requirement for significant cases heard by Commissioners fulfill the State archives requirements without the need to retain an additional discretionary sample.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>3.	The Court advised that cases heard by commissioners can be as significant as those heard by judges. The criteria for heritage listed trees is consistent with the disposal authorities for local government and the National Parks &amp; Wildlife Service. Examples of controversial cases are the illegal removal and poisoning of multiple trees to allow for better views.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph><Emphasis>Class 3 case files (land tenure, valuation, rating and compensation matters). Required as State archives</Emphasis>.	Entry 1.6.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Change</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>1.	Removal of random sampling (first 500 cases heard from 1980) as a criterion to determine State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>2.	Removal of allowance for a sample of files (illustrative of significant changes to the Court's jurisdiction, practice and procedure, or the nature of the cases bought before it and their outcomes) at the discretion of the Court</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>3.	Currently all cases heard by a judge are required as State archives. In addition to this it is proposed that cases heard by a commissioner that are controversial and attract media interest will also be retained as State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Justification</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>1.	Random sampling is no longer seen as an appropriate method of determining State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>2.	Cases heard by a judge and the new requirement for significant cases heard by commissioners fulfill the State archives requirements without the need to retain an additional discretionary sample.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>3.	The Court advised that cases heard by commissioners can be as significant as those heard by judges. Examples of controversial cases are where there can be a difference of millions of dollars between what the Valuer General has valued a property at, and what the owner has valued the property at. In a recent case the Valuer General valued land at Byron Bay $8.3 million in 2022. This was reduced to $810,000 by a Commissioner of the Court.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Class 8 civil mining matters. Required as State archives. </Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Change</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Expansion of scope of entry to cover Class 8 Civil mining matters. The Court did not hear these matters when FA228 was issued.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Proceedings in Class 8 are disputes under the Mining Act and the Petroleum (Onshore) Act. As the Court only deals with 1 or 2 of these matters per year and mining can affect the environment, it is proposed that all Class 8 matters are retained as State archives.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph><Emphasis>Judges’ or commissioners’ bench books and notebooks. Retain until retirement of judge or commissioner, then destroy</Emphasis>. Entry 1.9.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Previously the bench books of the Chief Justice up to 1998 were required as State archives. It is now proposed that they be retained until the retirement of the judge. The scope of the class has also been expanded to cover commissioners’ bench books.	Consistency with decision applying to judges’ notebooks in the Supreme Court.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Benchmarking</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>The authority has been benchmarked against:<List><Item>Queensland Courts Sector Retention and Disposal Schedule (2014). Includes the Land Court, Land Appeal Court and Planning and Environment Court.</Item><Item>Victoria Supreme Court (2023), County Court (2022) and Civil and Administrative Tribunal (2016)</Item><Item>Western Australia: State Administrative Tribunal (2013)</Item><Item>Tasmania Magistrates Court (2019) and Supreme Court (2015)</Item><Item>Northern Territory Supreme Court Administration (2016).</Item></List></Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Queensland is the only jurisdiction that has a dedicated land and environment court.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>External consultation </Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>State Records NSW consulted with the following organisations. No changes were required to the draft.<List><Item>Museums of History NSW: sought clarification on the justification to retain cases involving heritage-listed trees as State archives (entry 1.4). This is consistent with the local government disposal authority, and is relevant to Objective 5 (Records document significant impacts of government decisions on the environment). </Item><Item>Museums of History NSW: queried the need to list Aboriginal Land claims in entry 1.6 as these are heard by a judge and therefore already required as State archives. It has been listed to ensure these records are required as State archives in case these matters are ever heard by commissioners. Retention of Aboriginal Land claim records as State archives is consistent with the disposal authorities for Crown Lands and the National Parks &amp; Wildlife Service.</Item><Item>Natural Resources Access Regulator: did not have any feedback or concerns.</Item><Item>Environmental Defenders Office: sent their thanks for being consulted and advised they would have liked to have contributed, however on account of very limited capacity, they were unable to make a submission. </Item><Item>Environment Protection Authority: the legal team had reviewed and are happy with the proposed draft. No changes were requested.</Item><Item>Maryanne Wiffen, Albury City Council (Local government representative on State Records NSW Public Sector Advisory Committee): Council is supportive of the recommended changes.</Item><Item>Ben Thomson, The Hills Shire Council (Local government representative on State Records NSW Public Sector Advisory Committee): feedback had been sought from the General Counsel, Group Manager – Development &amp; Compliance, and the General Manager. Overall, Council welcomed the review and appreciated the efforts State Records NSW has taken to revise the authority. Council did not have any concerns. </Item><Item>NSW Department of Planning, Department of Communities and Justice, Court Services, the Supreme Court, Office of Local Government and the Shires Associations did not respond to the request for comment.</Item></List></Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Ms Sarah Froh, the Director and Registrar, Land and Environment Court, has advised the nominated minimum retention periods and disposal actions meet current legal and statutory obligations and the administrative requirements of the organisation.</Paragraph>
    </ContextContent>
  </Context>
  <Term type="function" itemno="1.0" update="2024-10-18">
    <TermTitle>LAND AND ENVIRONMENT COURT OF NSW</TermTitle>
    <TermDescription>
      <Paragraph>The Land and Environment Court is a superior court of record and hears environmental, development, building and planning disputes. The Court's jurisdiction includes the following:</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 1: Environmental planning and protection appeals (merits review appeals)</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 2: Local government, trees and miscellaneous appeals (merits review appeals) </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 3: Land tenure, valuation, rating and compensation matters, including Aboriginal land claim cases (merits review appeals) </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 4: Environmental planning and protection (civil enforcement and judicial review) </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 5: Environmental planning and protection (summary criminal enforcement) </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 6: Appeals against convictions or sentences relating to environmental offences (appeals as of right from decisions of a lower Court in prosecutions for environmental offences)</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 7: Appeals against convictions or sentences relating to environmental offences (appeals requiring leave from decisions of a lower Court in prosecutions for environmental offences)</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Class 8: Civil proceedings under mining legislation.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph><Emphasis>Note:</Emphasis> State Records NSW does not compel destruction of records after the minimum retention period.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph><Emphasis>Note:</Emphasis> Exhibits and original documents that are received by the Court but not ordered to remain as part of the Court file at the conclusion of the matter are not considered to be State records and should be returned to the owner, or disposed of by the Court where the owner cannot be identified.</Paragraph>
    </TermDescription>
    <Class itemno="1.1" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Key records of the administration of the Land and Environment Court. Includes:<List><Item>summary records and indexes of all matters commenced</Item><Item>judgements and conciliation statements from alternative dispute resolution</Item><Item>the formulation and establishment of policy, rules, practice directions and practice notes. </Item></List></Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination:</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 5. Records document significant impacts of government decisions on the environment.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decisions of 2006.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Consistent with Victoria, Queensland, Tasmania and Western Australia.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. These records provide a history of matters heard by the Land and Environment Court over time.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.10 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.11 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.12 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.13 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.3.1 - no change</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.2" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Case files for matters commenced in<Emphasis> Class 1</Emphasis> that have been:<List><Item>heard and decided by a Judge</Item><Item>heard by a Commissioner but relate to developments that are significant due to the fact they are a recipient of a State, national or international architectural or design award, are an important local or regional landmark, relate to heritage listed properties, are controversial or attract media interest.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Includes transcripts, documents filed by the parties, produced under subpoena and documents generated by the Court or judicial officer in relation to the case. </Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 5. Records document significant impacts of government decisions on the environment.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 for matters heard by a judge.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Queensland retain all matters as State archives.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: Previously matters heard by a commissioner in Class 1 were retained for 12 years after commencement of matter, unless they related to a development application, in which they were required to be retained by the Court. </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The Court advised that cases heard by commissioners can be as significant as those heard by judges. It is now proposed to retain matters heard by a commissioner that relate to award winning or controversial developments, important local or regional landmarks, or heritage listed properties, as State archives.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Previously a sample of the first 500 cases commenced from the inception of the Court, and a sample of cases (at the discretion of the Court) illustrating significant changes to procedures, practice or nature of cases were retained as State archives. The sampling has been removed. Cases heard by a judge and the new requirement for significant cases heard by commissioners fulfill the State archives requirements without the need to retain an additional discretionary sample.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.2 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.3 - removed sampling of first 500 cases from 1980</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.4 - removed random sampling</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.3" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Case files for matters in <Emphasis>Class 1</Emphasis> that:<List><Item>are heard and decided by a Commissioner but do not relate to significant developments, are not an important local or regional landmark, are not heritage listed or not controversial</Item><Item>were finalised before hearing. </Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Includes transcripts, documents filed by the parties, produced under subpoena and documents generated by the Court or judicial officer in relation to the case. </Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <RetentionPeriod unit="years">12</RetentionPeriod>
        <DisposalTrigger>commencement of matter</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 for most matters heard by a commissioner and matters finalised before a hearing.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: Previously Class 1 development application matters heard by a commissioner had to be retained by the Court with no approval to destroy (retain in agency). It is now proposed that significant development application matters will be retained as State archives under entry 1.2, and more routine cases for 12 years after commencement of the matter under this entry.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The Court is not the consent authority, and the records created and managed by the consent authority (usually a local council or NSW Planning) are either required as State archives or retained for at least 7 years after the structure is demolished. The Court has no business need to retain these files on an ongoing basis</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.6 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.7 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.5 - change from retain in agency to 12 years after commencement of the matter</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.4" update="2025-01-08">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Case files for matters commenced in <Emphasis>Class 2 </Emphasis>that:<List><Item>have been heard and decided by a Judge</Item><Item>have been heard by a Commissioner but relate to heritage listed trees or trees located within the curtilage of an item on the State Heritage Register.</Item><Item>are controversial or attract media interest.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Includes transcripts, documents filed by the parties, produced under subpoena and documents generated by the Court or judicial officer in relation to the case. </Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 5. Records document significant impacts of government decisions on the environment.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 for matters heard by a judge.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Queensland retain all matters as State archives.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change to matters heard by a judge. </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Previously no matters heard by a commissioner were required as State archives. The Court advised that cases heard by commissioners can be as significant as those heard by judges. It is now proposed to retain as State archives matters that are heard by a commissioner that relate to heritage listed trees or are controversial.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The criteria for heritage listed trees is consistent with the disposal authorities for local government and the National Parks &amp; Wildlife Service. Examples of controversial cases are the illegal removal and poisoning of multiple trees to allow for better views. Usually, State Records NSW avoids the use of controversy as a criterion, but the Court has advised that they can implement this.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Previously a sample of the first 500 cases commenced in class 2 from the inception of the Court, and a sample of cases illustrating significant changes to procedures, practice or nature of cases were retained as State archives. This random sampling has been removed. Cases heard by a judge and the new requirement for significant cases heard by commissioners fulfill the State archives requirements without the need to retain an additional discretionary sample.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><Emphasis>Board meeting 11 December</Emphasis>: the Board requested the wording 'or trees located within the curtilage of an item on the State Heritage Register' be added to the second dot point. The Land and Environment Court agreed to the addition.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.2 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.3 - removed sampling of first 500 cases from 1980</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.4 - removed random sampling</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.5" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Case files for matters in <Emphasis>Class 2</Emphasis> that:<List><Item>are heard and decided by a Commissioner but do not relate to relate to heritage listed trees or trees located within the curtilage of an item on the State Heritage Register, or are not controversial</Item><Item>were finalised before hearing. </Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Includes transcripts, documents filed by the parties, produced under subpoena and documents generated by the Court or judicial officer in relation to the case. </Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <RetentionPeriod unit="years">12</RetentionPeriod>
        <DisposalTrigger>commencement of matter</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 for most matters heard by a commissioner and matters finalised before a hearing.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: 	</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: Previously all matters heard by commissioners had a minimum retention period of 12 years after commencement of the matter. This has been narrowed to cases that do not relate to heritage listed trees or are not controversial. This will allow cases heard by commissioners that relate to heritage – listed trees or controversial matters to be retained as State archives under entry 1.4. </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><Emphasis>Board meeting 11 December</Emphasis>: the Board requested the wording 'or trees located within the curtilage of an item on the State Heritage Register' be added to the second dot point of entry 1.4. The Land and Environment Court agreed to the addition. This wording hs also been added to this entry.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.6 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.7 - no change</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.6" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Case files for matters commenced in <Emphasis>Class 3</Emphasis> that:<List><Item>are heard by a Judge</Item><Item>relate to Aboriginal land claims</Item><Item>are heard by a Commissioner but relate to controversial matters or attract media interest.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Includes transcripts, documents filed by the parties, produced under subpoena and documents generated by the Court or judicial officer in relation to the case. </Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 2. Records provide evidence of the identity of individuals and groups, their right to participate in the affairs of the State and make claim to entitlements and protection provided by the State and the administration of interests in land / real property.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 for matters heard by a judge.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Queensland retain all matters as State archives.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change to matters heard by a judge, which includes Aboriginal Land claims.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Previously no matters heard by a commissioner were required as State archives. The Court advised that cases heard by commissioners can be as significant as those heard by judges. It is now proposed to retain as State archives matters that are heard by a commissioner that are controversial.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Examples of controversial cases are where there can be a difference of millions of dollars between what the Valuer General has valued a property at, and what the owner has valued the property at. In a recent case the Valuer General valued land at Byron Bay $8.3 million in 2022. This was reduced to $810,000 by a commissioner of the Court.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Previously a sample of the first 500 cases commenced in class 3 from the inception of the Court, and a sample of cases illustrating significant changes to procedures, practice or nature of cases were retained as State archives. This random sampling has been removed. Cases heard by a judge and the new requirement for significant cases heard by commissioners fulfill the State archives requirements without the need to retain an additional discretionary sample.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.2 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.3 - removed sampling of first 500 cases from 1980</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.4 - removed random sampling</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.7" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Case files for matters in<Emphasis> Class 3</Emphasis> that:<List><Item>are heard and decided by a Commissioner but are not controversial</Item><Item>were finalised before hearing.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Includes transcripts, documents filed by the parties, produced under subpoena and documents generated by the Court or judicial officer in relation to the case. </Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <RetentionPeriod unit="years">12</RetentionPeriod>
        <DisposalTrigger>commencement of matter</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>PBasis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 for most matters heard by a commissioner and matters finalised before a hearing.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: Previously all matters heard by commissioners had a minimum retention period of 12 years after commencement of the matter. This has been narrowed to cases that are not controversial. Controversial matters heard by commissioners are now proposed for retention as State archives under entry 1.6.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.6 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.7 - no change</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.8" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Case files for all matters commenced in the following classes:<List><Item>Class 4: Environmental planning and protection (civil enforcement and judicial review) </Item><Item>Class 5: Environmental planning and protection (summary criminal enforcement) </Item><Item>Class 6: Appeals against convictions or sentences relating to environmental offences (appeals as of right from decisions of a lower court in prosecutions for environmental offences)</Item><Item>Class 7: Appeals against convictions or sentences relating to environmental offences (appeals requiring leave from decisions of a lower court in prosecutions for environmental offences)</Item><Item>Class 8: Civil proceedings under mining legislation. </Item></List></Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 5. Records document significant impacts of government decisions on the environment.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 for Classes 4, 5, 6 and 7.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Queensland retains all matters as State archives.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: Scope expanded to address a gap in coverage for Class 8 mining matters. These proceedings are disputes under the Mining Act and the Petroleum (Onshore) Act. As the Court only deals with 1 or 2 of these matters per year and mining can affect the environment, it is proposed that all Class 8 matters are retained as archives.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.1 - no change except for addition of Class 8 mining matters</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.9" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Judges or commissioner’s bench books and notebooks. </Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalTrigger>retirement of judge or commissioner</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006 except for bench books of the Chief Justice up to 1998. Consistent with NSW Supreme Court.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark:<List><Item>Victoria retains for 5 years after last entry.</Item><Item>Western Australia retains for 12 years after last entry.</Item><Item>Tasmania retains for 25 years after last entry.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: Previously the notebooks of the Chief Justice up to 1998 were required as State archives. Some of these (the notebooks of CJ McClelland and CJ Cripps are already held as State archives). </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The decisions of the Judges and Commissioners of the Court are contained in case files. Documents such as bench books and notebooks are only of use to each decision-maker and do not need to be retained by the Court after that judge or commissioner has left the Court. This is consistent with the disposal authority for the Supreme Court.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.17 - no change</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.16 - change from State archives to retirement of judge for bench books of Chief Justice C J Pearlman up to 1998.</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.10" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Routine records of the operations of the Court. Includes:<List><Item>daily and weekly listing records and case statistics</Item><Item>recordings of transcripts from proceedings ordered by parties but not collected. </Item><Item>recordings of telephone proceedings or online forums etc.</Item></List></Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalTrigger>administrative or reference use ceases</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent:</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark:<List><Item>Consistent with NSW and Victoria for court listings and recordings.</Item><Item>Northern Territory retain daily hearing lists for 5 years after date of hearing.</Item><Item>Queensland retains court listings for 2 years</Item><Item>Tasmania retains audio recordings for 3 months</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: Previously these records were retained for between 6 months and 5 years. Entries have been consolidated to streamline the authority. Transcripts or summary records of the proceedings and online forums are captured on the main court file</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.15 - change from 5 years to administrative and reference use ceases</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.18 - change from 6 months after delivery to Court registry to until administrative or reference use ceases</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.1.19 - change from 2 years after the date of the callover to until reference use ceases</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.11" update="2024-12-12">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Requests for information about the practice and procedure of the Court, e.g. enquiries by and replies to objectors.</Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <RetentionPeriod unit="years">5</RetentionPeriod>
        <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for determination</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2006.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark:<List><Item>Western Australia retains for between 2 and 7 years.</Item><Item>Tasmania retains for 2 years.</Item><Item>Northern Territory retains for 3 years.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/remarks: No change</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">FA228 1.2.1 - no change</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
  </Term>
</Authority>
