<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Authority xmlns="http://www.records.nsw.gov.au/schemas/RDA">
  <ID control="SRFileNo">SR2024/59</ID>
  <ID control="AR">565</ID>
  <ID control="FA">448</ID>
  <AuthorityTitle>Border fence maintenance</AuthorityTitle>
  <Scope>Border fence maintenance</Scope>
  <Status>
    <Draft version="2">
      <Agency agencyno="1127">Border Fence Maintenance Board</Agency>
      <Date>2024-06-18</Date>
    </Draft>
    <Approved>2024-09-25</Approved>
    <Issued>
      <Agency agencyno="1127">Border Fence Maintenance Board</Agency>
      <Date>2024-10-08</Date>
    </Issued>
  </Status>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.1.1 - Covered by GA28 10.3.1 No changes</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.1.2 - Covered by GA28 10.3.2 (B). No changes</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.3.2 - Covered by GA28 16.7.3. No change</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.1.1 - Covered by GA28 19.15.3. No changes</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.1.3 - Covered by GA28 14.4.4. No changes</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.2.5 - Covered by GA28 2.13.1. No changes</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.3.1 - Covered by GA28 19.15.3. No changes</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.3.4 - see GA28 14.4.4 no change</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.4.1 - see FA423 1.2.3. Change from 7 years after expiry to 10 years after expiry of 10 years after action, whichever is longer</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.4.2 - see FA423 1.2.3. Change from 1 years after last action to 10 years after expiry of 10 years after action, whichever is longer</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.3.2 - see GA28 13.4.1 no change</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.1.2 - see FA399</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.1.4 - see FA399</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.1.5 - legacy records of bounties paid. If any  records found can use GA28 FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.2.1 - see FA399 1.9.1. No changes</LinkedTo>
  <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.2.2 - see FA399 1.9.3. Decrease from 10 years to 3 years</LinkedTo>
  <Context type="appraisal report">
    <ContextTitle>Background</ContextTitle>
    <ContextContent>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Background</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>The Border Fence Maintenance Board aims to protect the Western Division pastoral industry, especially sheep grazing, from destruction caused by dingoes and wild dogs. To this end, the Board maintains a dog proof fence for 571 kilometres along the borders of South Australia and Queensland. It previously managed programs aimed at actively controlling wild dogs and dingoes within the Western Division (below) through the payment of a bounty on scalps.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph> The Board was established in 1958 as the Wild Dog Destruction Board and was renamed the Border Fence Maintenance Board in 2017. The Board has six members, including the Chairperson, who is the Commissioner. The other five members are all resident pastoral landholders of the Western Division of NSW. The Board operates from an office in Broken Hill and its small staff mostly consists of fence maintenance officers who patrol and maintain the fence.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Submission</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Request for approval of revised retention and disposal authorisation for the function of border fence maintenance.</Paragraph>
      <Source>Annual reports of the Wild Dog Destruction Board, 1992, 1999, 2022</Source>
      <Source>State Records control system</Source>
    </ContextContent>
  </Context>
  <Context type="appraisal report">
    <ContextTitle>Issue</ContextTitle>
    <ContextContent>
      <Paragraph>The Board uses FA265 which was issued in 2008 and is due for review. The authority has been streamlined from 28 entries to 13 entries with the removal of records covered by the General retention and disposal authority: administrative records (GA28). The Board very occasionally issues permits to keep dingoes as pets. These are covered by the National Parks &amp; Wildlife Service disposal authority.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Benchmarking</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>The draft has been benchmarked against the following disposal authorities:<List><Item>South Australia: Local Government Records (2019)</Item><Item>Queensland: Agriculture (2015)</Item><Item>Tasmania: Department of Primary Industry, Parks, Water &amp; Environment (2008)</Item><Item>Northern Territory: Sustainable Land Management Records (2006)</Item></List></Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        <Emphasis>Consultation</Emphasis>
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Feedback was sought from:<List><Item>Museums of History NSW</Item><Item>Local Land Services</Item><Item>Soil Conservation Service</Item><Item>Crown Lands NSW</Item><Item>Office of Environment and Heritage</Item><Item>Wild Dog Barrier Fence Panel of Queensland</Item><Item>The Dog Fence Board of South Australia</Item></List></Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Museums of History NSW was favourable to the draft and had no changes. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Local Land Services asked for confirmation that non-residual chemicals were used to control weeds (entry 1.3). If residual chemicals were used, Local Land Services suggested the minimum retention period needed to be increased. The Board has confirmed that non-residual chemicals are used. A note has been added to say that residual chemicals are addressed under GA28, which requires the retention of records of risk management of exposure to toxic chemicals for 75 years.</Paragraph>
    </ContextContent>
  </Context>
  <Term type="function" itemno="1.0" update="2024-09-12">
    <TermTitle>BORDER FENCE MANAGEMENT</TermTitle>
    <TermDescription>
      <Paragraph>The function of managing the dog proof fence to exclude wild dogs from grazing lands of the Western Division of NSW.</Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>Includes taking action against landholders and other offenders not complying with regulations.</Paragraph>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="FA">399</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Local land Services</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the management of wild dog control programs.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="FA">423</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>National parks and wildlife</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>AUTHORISATION</TermTitleRef>
        <ItemNoRef>1.2.3</ItemNoRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to permits to keep dingos</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative Records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>CONTRACTING-OUT</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the contracting-out or outsourcing of construction work including contracts.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Agreements</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to agreement with other governments in relation to the construction and maintenance of the dog proof fence.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>LEGAL SERVICES</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Litigation</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to managing lawsuits or legal proceedings between the organisation and other parties in a court or other tribunal.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>OCCUPATIONAL HEALTH &amp; SAFETY</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Compliance</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to poisons used to control weeds.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative Records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the erection, management and leasing-out of the boundary rider cottages.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative Records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Conservation</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the remediation of contaminated land and the conservation of Aboriginal sites.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative Records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Construction</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to minor works, project management of construction works and the identification and management of hazardous materials (such as asbestos) used or encountered in construction work.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Maintenance</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to routine maintenance such as painting, cleaning, maintenance etc</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative Records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>PROPERTY MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Planning</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the planning of construction programs.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative Records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>TENDERING</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to receiving and assessing tenders for construction work.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
    </TermDescription>
    <Comment author="SRNSW">
      <Paragraph>Justifications/Remarks: The board has only recieved 1 application to keep dingos in the past 10 years. The Board still administers permits in the Western Division under the Companion Animals Act 1998 No 87. Added unsuccessful application for streamlining the document.</Paragraph>
    </Comment>
    <Class update="2024-10-08" itemno="1.1">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Key records relating to the design, construction, major renovation or restoration of the dog proof fence, e.g. building and development applications and supporting documents, plans/designs, specifications, photographs, drawings etc.</Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for decision</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Building the archives policy: Objective 4. Records relate to places of significance to the broader community and the State of NSW.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Consistent with General retention and disposal authority: administrative records (GA28) for design and construction records of landmark structures.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justifications/Remarks: No change.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.3.1 - no change</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class update="2024-10-08" itemno="1.2">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Records relating to the granting of easements to the organisation by third parties for the purpose of maintaining the dog proof fence.</Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <RetentionPeriod unit="years">10</RetentionPeriod>
        <DisposalTrigger>cancellation or termination of easement</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for decision</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Granting of easements retained for 7 years after extinguishment in the General retention and disposal authority: local government records, and for 20 years after extinguishment in the National Parks &amp; Wildlife disposal authority. </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Records are required for a certain period of time after easement is cancelled or terminated as evidence the Board had rights to access property.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.1.3 - no change</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="1.3" update="2024-10-08">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Records relating to operational management of the dog proof fence. Includes:<List><Item>consultation and communication with landholders, including informal advice and discussions, notifications of maintenance works along the dog proof fence</Item><Item>measures for the control of weeds and wild dogs along the dog proof fence, including measures taken in conjunction with other authorities such as the National Parks and Wildlife Service, e.g. documentation of method of control, dates control undertaken, records of effectiveness of control and neighbour notification notices.</Item><Item>control and use of vehicle access ways along the dog proof fence, e.g. requests for permission to travel along the dog proof fence and responses to those requests</Item><Item>minor construction works</Item><Item>brochures, posters, training materials etc.</Item><Item>detailed advice provided to the public</Item><Item>issuing of notices for breaches of legislation, e.g. investigations, copies of notices, copies of fines issued, correspondence, etc.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><Emphasis>Note: </Emphasis>this entry covers the use of non-residual chemicals. If chemicals are used where there is a risk to employees use <Source>General retention and disposal authority: administrative records: </Source>OCCUPATIONAL HEALTH &amp; SAFETY – Risk management.</Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
        <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for decision</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Consistent with the General retention and disposal authority: local government records for issue of notices, minor construction works and advice. Consistent with Local Land Services for liaison and advice. Control of weeds and pests are retained for 2 years in the General retention and disposal authority: administrative records (GA28).</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark:<List><Item>Consistent with Tasmania.</Item><Item>South Australia retains for between 6 and 10 years after action completed.</Item><Item>Northern Territory retains for 4 years after action completed for advice and discussion regarding land management issues. </Item><Item>Queensland retains for 10 years after business completed. Consistent with Queensland relating to destruction orders.</Item></List></Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justifications/Remarks: Previously these records were retained for between 6 and 7 years, or 10 years for vehicle access. To streamline the authority a 7-year retention period has been adopted. This retention period meets the Board's requirements to retain these records as potential evidence relating to dealings or agreements with landholders.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The monitoring of wild dog control by landowners and the payment of bounties for wild dog scalps are no longer functions undertaken by the Board as they were removed from the Act in 2017. Some legacy records may still exist. The Board’s latest annual reports notes that there were very few sightings of wild dogs along the fence, but baits are laid along the fence to control them.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.2.1 - increase from 6 to 7</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.3.3 - increase from 6 to 7</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">1.4.1 - reduced from 10 to 7</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.2.3 - change from 10 to 7 years</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.2.4 - change from 6 to 7</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.3.4 - change from 6 years to 7 years</LinkedTo>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">3.3.3 - Change from 15 years to 7 years</LinkedTo>
      <Comment author="SRNSW">
        <Paragraph>Still 3 years under the Pesticides Act.</Paragraph>
      </Comment>
      <Comment author="SRNSW">
        <Paragraph>monitoring of wild dog control by landholders including copies of notices requiring landholders to undertake the destruction of wild dogs. - undertaken by LLS not the Board</Paragraph>
      </Comment>
      <Comment author="SRNSW">
        <Paragraph>bounties paid for the scalps of wild dogs destroyed in the Western Division. - no longer in Act. Removed in 2017</Paragraph>
      </Comment>
    </Class>
  </Term>
  <Term type="function" itemno="2.0" update="2024-09-12">
    <TermTitle>RATES</TermTitle>
    <TermDescription>
      <Paragraph>The function of regulating the rates payable by landholders in the Western Division to the organisation.</Paragraph>
      <SeeReference>
        <IDRef control="GA">28</IDRef>
        <AuthorityTitleRef>Administrative records</AuthorityTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT</TermTitleRef>
        <TermTitleRef>Accounting</TermTitleRef>
        <SeeText>for records relating to the organisation’s financial
 transactions.</SeeText>
      </SeeReference>
    </TermDescription>
    <Comment author="Angela">
      <Paragraph>rates are payable to maintain the fence?</Paragraph>
    </Comment>
    <Class itemno="2.1" update="2024-10-08">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Records relating to the setting and amendment of rates. This includes the general waiving of rates, for example during periods of drought. Records include investigations and policy determinations, draft rate schedules, and government and community consultation undertaken as part of the process.</Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalAction>Required as State archives</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for decision</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Building the archives: Objective 3. Records are essential for the evidence of fundamental rights and entitlements of individuals within the community regarding the setting of rates.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Consistent with the setting of local government rates by IPART.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. These records document issues affecting landholders of the Western Division.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Only land in the Western Division where the aggregation of the holding exceeds 1000 hectares is subject to payment of dog rates. The Board sets the annual dog rate having regard to the annual budgeted cost of maintaining the fence, less any contribution from the State Government. For example, in 2021 the NSW Government paid an amount of $429,170.00 to the Border Fence Maintenance Board and landholder rates were set at 5.5 cents per hectare for the 2022 year.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">2.1.1 - no changes</LinkedTo>
    </Class>
    <Class update="2024-10-08" itemno="2.2">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Records relating to objections to rates or applications for hardship relief, whether successful or unsuccessful. Records include applications and objections, records of internal advice associated with the matter, correspondence with applicants, determinations, and terms of repayment.</Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <RetentionPeriod unit="years">7</RetentionPeriod>
        <DisposalTrigger>action completed</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for decision</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008. Consistent with similar records managed by NSW local government for objections to Council rates.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Tasmania retains for 7 years after action completed for successful applications and 2 years for unsuccessful.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change. Crown Lands NSW issues the rate notices and undertakes debt recovery on behalf of the Board. These records are covered by the General retention and disposal authority: administrative records and are retained for 7 years.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">2.1.2 - no changes</LinkedTo>
      <Comment author="SRNSW">
        <Paragraph>Conistent with FA399 1.11.2</Paragraph>
      </Comment>
      <Comment author="Angela">
        <Paragraph>FA253 superseded. This retention period is consistent with a similar class in Functional Retention and Disposal Authority FA253 - Crown Lands Management.</Paragraph>
      </Comment>
    </Class>
    <Class itemno="2.3" update="2024-10-08">
      <ClassDescription>
        <Paragraph>Records relating to the implementation of rates schedules. Includes records of procedures for the calculation, determination and levying of rates and the issuing of schedules, and reports received from other government agencies on the collection of rates.</Paragraph>
      </ClassDescription>
      <Disposal>
        <DisposalTrigger>superseded</DisposalTrigger>
        <DisposalAction>Destroy</DisposalAction>
      </Disposal>
      <Justification>
        <Paragraph>Basis for decision</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Precedent: Confirms Board decision of 2008.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Benchmark: Nil.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Justification/Remarks: No change.</Paragraph>
      </Justification>
      <LinkedTo type="linking table">2.1.3 - no changes</LinkedTo>
      <Comment author="Rianna">
        <Paragraph>Elected to reamin in although covered by GA28 19.16.1 and 7.1.1 for ease of use by agency.</Paragraph>
      </Comment>
    </Class>
  </Term>
</Authority>
